<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	
	<title type="text" xml:lang="en"></title>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" href="http://rpietro.github.io/feed/" rel="self"/>
 	<link type="text" href="hhttp://rpietro.github.io/" rel="alternate"/>
	<updated>2013-09-25T11:00:11-04:00</updated>
	<id>http://http://rpietro.github.io/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Ricardo Pietrobon</name>
	</author>
	<rights>Copyright (c) 2013, Ricardo Pietrobon; all rights reserved.</rights>
	
	
	<entry>
		<title>Orientando pesquisadores: O começo de uma série de artigos</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/28/coaching_posts/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/28/coaching_posts</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-NFPD8IREMX4/UkLT_E35bCI/AAAAAAAA4Uk/VdQPKKT90To/w805-h403-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estou começando uma série de posts que sobre sugestões práticas para pesquisadores. Minha experiência decorre de ter &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=F5m0nQoAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;publicado em pesquisas clínica&lt;/a&gt; por muitos anos, além de ter conduzido um programa de treinamento focado em professores juniores na Duke University e algumas outras instituições. Isso significa que os posts frequentemente vão usar exemplos relacionados com a área biomédica e análise de dados, mas acredito que a maioria do conteúdo pode ser extrapolado para outras áreas de pesquisa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cada uma destes posts estará disponível em Inglês e Português, geralmente postados em dias consecutivos. Os posts também serão publicados nas respectivas paginas do Facebook, nas suas versões global e brasileira, a página brasileira &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/578812732155954/?bookmark_t=group&quot;&gt;já estando disponível&lt;/a&gt;. Outras línguas podem vir a aparecer posteriormente caso os posts gerem interesse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mas chega de conversa, mãos a obra ...&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Beginning a series of posts</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/27/coaching_posts/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/27/coaching_posts</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-NFPD8IREMX4/UkLT_E35bCI/AAAAAAAA4Uk/VdQPKKT90To/w805-h403-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am starting a series of posts I plan on publishing about practical suggestions for researchers. My experience stems from having &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=F5m0nQoAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;published in clinical and health services research&lt;/a&gt; for many years, as well as having run a coaching program targeting junior faculty members at Duke University and a few other institutions. All this means is that my posts will frequently use examples related to the biomedical and data sciences, but I also believe that most of the content can be extrapolated to other research areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these posts will be available in English and Portuguese versions, usually posted in consecutive days. They will also be published to the respective Global and Brazilian versions of a Facebook Group page, the Brazilian page [already being available]](https://www.facebook.com/groups/578812732155954/?bookmark_t=group). Other languages might follow depending on whether the posts generate some interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough said, let&amp;#39;s get to work ...&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>GiveDirectly libations</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/26/givedirectly_libations/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/26/givedirectly_libations</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LJRJzeuK15Q/Ujx5wKJIJFI/AAAAAAAA4LE/C4LZ_gPyNHU/w707-h481-no/fractals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ve probably heard of people who floss in the shower just because it creates an automatic habit. So, along &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.brandeis.edu/%7Eteuber/singermag1.html&quot;&gt;Peter Singer&amp;#39;s proposal&lt;/a&gt; that we should all donate money to people who didn&amp;#39;t have the same opportunities we did, I am proposing the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/give.php&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; libations. Here is how it works: You simply place the GiveDirectly link on the top of your bookmark, making it visible at all times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Qr-jEqqbGuo/Ujx2socEoMI/AAAAAAAA4Kk/rxMBxUOShwU/w454-h141-no/Screen+Shot+2013-09-20+at+12.23.12+PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, every time you feel like you have to ask your gods for support or strength or hope or simply luck, you go ahead and make a GiveDirectly libation by donating some money. The quantity is proportional to how much you might want to get your gods on your side, some of them might be picky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly is one of the best donation sites, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/give.php&quot;&gt;90 to 93% of your donation being transferred to the people who need the money&lt;/a&gt;. This will allow them to buy food, get better shelter, learn something, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givedirectly.org/faqs.php&quot;&gt;do whatever they think their top priority might be&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Shinto, situated cognition, and monism</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/25/shinto_monism_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/25/shinto_monism_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--0Nq3O2KBnQ/Ujpbfxsl2NI/AAAAAAAA4JM/T2C3ycZ6gWY/w480-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An upfront disclosure: I am agnostic. By that I mean that I am indifferent to whether gods might or not exist, whether there might be something after what we know as life, and other concepts that are typically attributed to the realm of religion. An important distinction, I am not an atheist, meaning that I don&amp;#39;t deny the existence of gods. I am simply indifferent: Whether they might or not exist is simply not a concern of mine. But in being agnostic I have a deep respect for the power religion has on human beings and how deeply it affects literally all of us, whether you might follow any religion, be atheist or an agnostic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that disclosure out of the way, one of the most interesting concepts I&amp;#39;ve found in religious movements is the idea of integration with the whole universe. I was first introduced to the concept during a period in which I practiced &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aikido&quot;&gt;Aikido&lt;/a&gt; for a year or so. Every class had a practice of the martial art as a physical exercise, but also short lectures on the importance of being integrated with the universe in order to execute the Aikido movements. Briefly, one of the main concepts behind Aikido is that you don&amp;#39;t fight &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; somebody, but you instead let the energy of your opponents be directed against them. In order to do this, as my Aikido instructor always said, when the energy comes to you, you simply dissipate it by letting it go through. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How effective Aikido is as a martial art for street fighting is beyond the point of this post, but the point I want to make is that the concept of being integrated with the universe and participating in an overarching energy flow seem to have gotten to Aikido from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shinto&quot;&gt;Shinto&lt;/a&gt;. The concept is actually spread to a number of areas that have no connection to either Shinto or Aikido, a very recent example being &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkour&quot;&gt;Parkour&lt;/a&gt;, where people get through city barriers such as eight feet walls not by attacking them but actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aAhPaiajwDY&quot;&gt;moving in harmony with them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps what is common to Aikido, Shinto and Parkour is the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monism&quot;&gt;Monism&lt;/a&gt;, or the concept that there is a unity that is inherent to all things. Where learning comes into the scene, I think, is with the concepts of using &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situated_cognition&quot;&gt;situated cognition&lt;/a&gt; permeate the learning process. I have covered some of these concepts in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/07/29/shallows_medieval/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, but one example would be that learning is not about simply absorbing concepts, but it is instead about interacting with your environment to produce some kind of outcome. For example, rather than just learning a programming language, students will also learn how to properly ask other programmers for help or how to search for the latest tools that might help beyond what they learned during the course. In another situation, rather than simply learning about, say, racial disparities, one would take a course as an opportunity to be coached while actively working with a community to address sources of disparity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point in all of this is that the distinction between the concepts underlying religion, the sciences, humanities and likely anything humans touch is very subtle. Perhaps this is why I think that those strongly arguing in favor of a certain religion or against all religions are probably mistaken. Just look around and you will see religious concepts permeating all we do, learning included.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Merrienboer, whole tasks and the learning ladder</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/24/sequencing_ladder/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/24/sequencing_ladder</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-9M89ShrDfCI/UjnxONF95nI/AAAAAAAA4H8/19ksRO9GP20/w480-h680-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/30/whole_task_ladder/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I have argued that while I agree with Merrienboer&amp;#39;s concept of whole tasks as an essential component in the learning process, as students increase their skill levels, they might need to step out of whole tasks to focus on narrower sectors of a given task. The latter is called a learning ladder, where experts receive only particular sectors of a given whole task where there are unusual problems. Because these problems are unusual, experts continue to accumulate experience with interesting problems, ultimately honing their skills even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I failed to mention, however, is that although the learning ladder and the whole task principle are somewhat at odds, the ladder certainly aligns with Merrieboer&amp;#39;s sequencing concept. In Merrienboer&amp;#39;s terminology, sequencing means that whole tasks should be made progressively more complex. What the learning ladder brings to the table is simply the practical realization that if complexity levels keep going up, it is no longer feasible for the student to focus on everything, but more practical to let other team members deal with the every day components of the whole task, while the expert deals with the unusual and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Need for evidence-based policy making in education</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/23/eb_policy_making/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/23/eb_policy_making</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-V2EmCX1ceMg/UjnxOXj6gJI/AAAAAAAA4IA/k88cluJk3Uk/w480-h680-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/81Ka8i8u43W&quot;&gt;posted something on Google plus&lt;/a&gt; where I argued that the sources behind educational policy making should contain at least some degree of data. In our day and age, it would be naive to think that policy making can be entirely based on data for at least a few reasons: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Policy-Making-Education-Holistic-Approach-Response/dp/1607091615/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1379477791&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=policy+making+in+education&quot;&gt;Studies have shown over and again&lt;/a&gt; that educational policy making is primarily driven by personal interests of those in the top ranks of each national government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We simply don&amp;#39;t have enough data, experimental or observational, to cover all the data needs to create evidence-based policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To think of data as something objective and interest-free is highly misguided. The very act of designing a data collection or experiment already contains an intention to &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/12/university_dilemma/&quot;&gt;demonstrate a few things and hide others&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these three points out of the way, I would argue that collecting some data using reproducible standards is at least something that can be criticized, while a mere opinion based on vested interests is hard to dissect. For example, if your data was collected in a reproducible manner I can criticize whatever aspect of it and try to do better, but if a politician simply states that something has to be done in a certain way because &lt;em&gt;that&amp;#39;s the right thing to do&lt;/em&gt;. The latter can&amp;#39;t be argued about since the person who stated it is the most powerful stakeholder in the decision making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Ben Gunn, social extension, and implications for learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/22/bengunn/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/22/bengunn</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-SvK1_5pQoGg/UjnxOdF3akI/AAAAAAAA4IE/Ccl-LgNEY1Q/w480-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently read a very interesting article where a journalist has interviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://prisonerben.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Ben Gunn&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, when Ben was 14 years old he killed another boy and was sentenced to 10 years in prison. Hi behavior while in jail was all but good, and 10 years were extended to the point where he was only released when he was 42. What is interesting about this is that while he was in jail he not only graduated from college, but went on to a MSc and started a PhD. In his blog he raises a fascinating discussion by lively describing situations he faced while in prison, making us question whether our prison system is doing society a service or just simply educating people to be better criminals than they were before getting into that system. His text is simply superb, which attracted the attention of not only about 20 thousand followers but also of newspapers and tv channels that now have Ben serving as an expert consultant every time an issue about the prison system is brought up. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/sep/15/ben-gunn-murder-love-life-after-prison&quot;&gt;full interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That whole story is already interesting in and of itself, but in the interview Ben raises a point that I find simply fascinating. He claims to be lost after having left prison, since he doesn&amp;#39;t understand the rules by which people play. Rules while in prison were clear, but outside why do we do the things we do? In other words, if you are a blogger with 20 thousand followers and consults for major news channels, why does it matter? In other words, what is the rat wheel in which society places us all to make us believe that the goals set for ourselves are worth pursuing? The interesting thing is that by Ben being an outsider and already an adult, it will be hard for him to buy into these fictitious reasons we keep fabricating for ourselves to get us out of bed in the morning. Ideas of meaning in our careers, or an ultimate goal that we keep pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the rat wheel/meaning topic is relevant for learning in at least two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social extension: No matter much we might believe that we are individually in charge of our own goals, we are not. What is perceived to be an individual goal of mine is almost certainly something that I inherited from society, society making me believe that my goal is worth pursuing. One interpretation then is that learning has to happen in a social context. It&amp;#39;s not enough to learn a skill or simply absorb information. Learning has to happen in a context that will make that information or skill to have our so desired sense of meaning. This can be accomplished by reinforcing the skills and information with a social context that will provide a role model and help student set their &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; goals that are in reality social goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to get out of the rat wheel: A different goal is to provide students with the ability to perceive that what might seem as an individual goal is in reality something that society makes them perceive as individuals, but which in reality is imposed. Now, it would be naive to think that learning could provide students with the ability to be free from societal influences. After all, we&amp;#39;re humans and our nature seems to be to follow the flock, but perhaps an education that would at least give us a hint of what it is to think outside of the rat wheel would be a good thing ... or lead to a huge anxiety level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Need for educational scores adjusted to socio-economic factors</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/21/adjusted_scores/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/21/adjusted_scores</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0IcrIVRSBlc/UjZmrIMKgHI/AAAAAAAA33g/omCU3nWv_r0/w1000-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oecd.org/&quot;&gt;OECD(Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development)&lt;/a&gt; has been releasing a number of statistics on education for many years. In their reports, comparisons are made across different countries in relation to, among many other things, the effectiveness of their national education systems. What we tend to forget, however, is that education is not an isolated factor, meaning that educational performance will depend on a number of socio-economic factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about this in the comments to one of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/59orarBgrRP&quot;&gt;posts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;, but the concept is that educational indices should be statistically adjusted to socio-economic factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me establish an analogy with healthcare: If I am a physician treating very sick patients, the complication rate of my patients will be substantially higher than those of somebody treating otherwise healthy patients. Does that mean that I am a bad doctor? No, simply means that my patients are sicker. Bringing this example back to education, the fact that a developing or emerging country has bad educational indices does not necessarily mean that they have a bad educational policy, but it might mean that they are doing the best possible job they can given the local socio-economic situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to generate these adjusted educational index, one would have to combine datasets containing information from education, economics, healthcare, and any other sources that might provide insight on factors that might downplay educational performance. Such a &lt;em&gt;Learning Observatory&lt;/em&gt; would have to have the ability to combine data in different formats (CSV, JSON, XML, free text, RDF, among others), always keeping in mind what the information needs of educational policy makers might be in order to put together policies aligned with their local situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Novice researchers learning how to conduct a literature review: An iterative zoom-in-out method</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/20/zoominout/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/20/zoominout</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-MAVte8M8bIE/UjY9EdKFlSI/AAAAAAAA328/ylvieZYqi70/w480-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most common mistakes made by a novice researcher when writing an original scientific paper is to write sections requiring a literature review one paper at a time. When they do this, it read like &amp;quot;author A said X,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;author B said Z,&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;author C said Z.&amp;quot; What is usually missing is not only the connection among each one of these statements but a true narrative telling a story that will connect with readers. Bear in mind, while on the surface we might sound like sophisticated scientists, in reality we are just the same cave men who gathered around the fire telling stories to each other for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, how does a novice researcher go from first getting acquainted with some papers in the field to a coherent and engaging narrative? What follows is an evolving method, and it is not trivial as it will require that you have a good level of technical sophistication. While I do plan on putting together a mini-course describing each step in detail, for now this is just an introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get to know the field before you write anything&lt;/em&gt;: First things first: Do not write the sections of the Introduction and Discussion sections of your paper before you have a good understanding of the literature. I know this sounds like a waste of time, but it will be easier in the end, trust me. One of the problems of writing a choppy, one paper at a time section is that once you commit to that kind of structure, it&amp;#39;s actually pretty hard to get out. Almost like a conceptual cage. Of importance, there is a sea of difference between the role and way you write the literature review for the Introduction and Discussion sections, but this is a topic I won&amp;#39;t cover now. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Define your initial set of concepts&lt;/em&gt;: The key for a smart search is to identify the kinds of concepts and their synonyms you would like to find. For example, I might want to find all the instances of the concepts &amp;quot;situated&amp;quot; within a certain proximity from the concept &amp;quot;cognition&amp;quot; and in articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proper software&lt;/em&gt;: Install a copy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://jabref.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;JabRef&lt;/a&gt;. While most academics nowadays use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zotero.org/&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mendeley.com/&quot;&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://endnote.com/&quot;&gt;Endnote&lt;/a&gt;, the main advantage of JabRef is that all your citations are stored as text files, and as I will describe later on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Agregate searches across bibliographic databases&lt;/em&gt;: Run web searches from within JabRef, using as many bibliographic databases as you think might be required. I won&amp;#39;t go over the details required to search within each one of them, which can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;http://jabref.sourceforge.net/help/Contents.php&quot;&gt;JabRef&amp;#39;s help page&lt;/a&gt; but by and large you will run boolean searches as you would on the original page. You can also run a search on the database page, export the search results as a file, and then import it into JabRef.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Store your citations as text files and then search using regexp and text mining functions&lt;/em&gt;: JabRef saves the full library as a .bib file, meaning that this is a text file. To search the full file, simply enter into regular expression mode and you will have a much more powerful search than you could have within JabRef or the original application. Take that same file and treat with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tm/vignettes/tm.pdf&quot;&gt;tm package&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; and you will have the ability to slice and dice your search in every single imaginable way. Of importance, go ahead and create a repo in &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Gihub&lt;/a&gt; so that you can version your search as well as allow your collaborators and others to fork it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Try to find the key papers to use in your Introduction or Discussion sections&lt;/em&gt;: Once regexp and text mining have given you tips on whether a certan paper might contain the type of information you want, evaluating its methodology should follow a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/How-Read-Paper-Evidence-Based-ebook/dp/B005D7EUBA/ref=tmm_kin_title_0&quot;&gt;regular evidence-based sequence&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than trying to exhaust the literature, a good rule of thumb is to find the three or four key articles in relation to that topic, read them carefully, and then check their citations and the papers that have cited them, obviously including the relevant ones to your JabRef text file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enrich the citations with full text articles of the key papers&lt;/em&gt;: Once you have identified the key papers for each topic, grab their HTML files saved as complete Web pages and paste those into the &lt;em&gt;Review&lt;/em&gt; field within RefJab. This will include the full text into your final .bib file, allowing you to run regexp and text mining methods also across the full text. Notice that for certain databases such as PubMed, full-text search is not available. The PDF for each article should also be store within RefJab, although you won&amp;#39;t use PDFs for your regexp/text mining. Last, for bibliographic databases having alert functionality, go ahead and set queries that will keep sending you additional references throughout the course of your project. One word of caution when storing full-text HTML in your bib files under GitHub is that you should not place copyrighted material under a public repo. So, if you have copyrighted full-text articles, simply use a private repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zoom in and out&lt;/em&gt;: From then on you will be constantly zooming out and looking at the conceptual map that you build as you read the key papers, and then zooming in to get the details of each key publication. The process is iterative and should probably last for the entire project lifecycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Markdown for learning materials</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/19/markdown/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/19/markdown</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-eQMPOpwIZDw/UjT9Wg3pPuI/AAAAAAAA31w/CahngnC1-0E/w1000-h500-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/basics&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is all the rage among geeks, but should educators even care? I would say that Markdown is an excellent option for educators who like to learn new things and don&amp;#39;t mind having a period where they might feel like working with their traditional tools made them more productive. Below are the main advantages, text below referring specifically to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/README.html&quot;&gt;Pandoc flavor of Markdown&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pure text: This might sound like a terrible reason, but being based on pure text rather than proprietary formats like MS Word has a number of advantages as will be outlined below. This does not mean that the final format is in plain text, since you can export the document to almost any type of file you can imagine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple export formats: Files in Markdown can be exported to PDF, slides, web pages in HTML, LaTeX, MS Word documents, among many others. This means that if you are writing a paper, but want to turn that paper into a Web page, you are just one click away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semi-automatic translation: Because the document is in pure text you can simply upload it to a tool like &lt;a href=&quot;http://translate.google.com/toolkit&quot;&gt;Google Translator Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;, have it automatically translated to another language of your choice, and then have a human translator make minor changes. Because all the formatting is created through characters like * or # or _ , your final format will maintained exactly as is, be that a PDF, slide presentation, word document, etc &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reuse: Because you use the exact same way of writing to articles, blog posts, slides, among others, it&amp;#39;s just natural that you will be looking through your old documents and reusing chunks of texts rather than writing them again. Actually, after some time you will probably find yourself creating chunks of text solely for the purpose of reusing them in multiple locations, but don&amp;#39;t worry about that for now, this will come naturally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semantic citations with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.essepuntato.it/lode/http://purl.org/spar/cito&quot;&gt;CiTO&lt;/a&gt;: Bibliographic citations in Markdown using the CiTO ontology means that when you cite a paper or a book, all the information about that reference will be available to you. In a traditional citation software, when you cite a reference you are able to see the usual info about authors, date of publication, etc, but in a semantic citation you would also have a connection to the abstract, databases that might have cited that reference, and any database that might connect to that reference in the future. All of this is obtained simply by adding the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doi.org/&quot;&gt;DOI (Digital Object Identifier)&lt;/a&gt; when you add the reference to your text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Math equations: In contrast with softwares such as Microsoft Word where a math equation might not display properly when you transform that page into a PDF or Web page, math formulas in Pandoc Markdown are consistently transformed across files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tables: Tables are not only extremely easy to put together, but if you are performing data analyses you can very easily have tables automatically populated. The advantage is that if you modify your analysis in any way, ultimately affecting every cell in the table, using Markdown all results will be automatically updated without the need to manually do each cell all over again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Styling CSS: Let&amp;#39;s say you have a collection of one thousand documents, and all of a sudden you decide that you want to change their look and feel. Using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3schools.com/css/&quot;&gt;cascading style sheets (CSS)&lt;/a&gt; the change can be made in a single document and then automatically spread to all documents. Of importance, this doesn&amp;#39;t work all that well for PDF, although there are some potential solutions to this problem with software such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.princexml.com/&quot;&gt;Prince XML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration with data analysis: As mentioned in the point about tables, it is fairly easy to integrate Markdown with statistical languages like &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; using packages such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://yihui.name/knitr/&quot;&gt;knitr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amazing slide presentations: Although Pandoc Markdown does have a way to generate slides, &lt;a href=&quot;http://slidify.org/&quot;&gt;Slidify&lt;/a&gt; has a number of advantages that justify going along with it: Support for many different presentation modes, quizzes, dynamic graphics, among many other features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is obviously more, but this probably good enough for a post. If you would like to give it a try, perhaps the best way is just to start using it in a tablet computer like the iPad, there are excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://ipad.appstorm.net/roundups/productivity-roundups/the-14-best-markdown-editors-and-notepads-for-the-ipad/&quot;&gt;review articles talking about different apps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Learning clinical research design using input-output concepts</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/18/design_input_output/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/18/design_input_output</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-2cJPhN7us9w/UjCwvtDuzeI/AAAAAAAA3yo/19xQIJVaVhw/w800-h500-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time clinical researchers and data science specialists have lived in separate worlds, where a data science specialist knows little about the clinical aspects of an analysis and the clinical research knows next to nothing about data analysis. Some people have called this a turf protection from the traditional statisticians&amp;#39; perspective, but in reality it&amp;#39;s just both sides shooting themselves in the foot. Rather than protecting turf, the lack of appropriate communication not only reduces the overall quality of the final work, but it also decreases the odds that the clinical research specialist will try to dig deeper into the vast array of techniques the data scientist might have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absurdity of this whole situation relied by and large on the idea that in some fields such as data sciences would either know everything and become &lt;em&gt;one of them&lt;/em&gt; or nothing at all. The problem with the proverbial &amp;quot;little knowledge&amp;quot; is that it might hold true when you are acting alone, but if you work in an interdisciplinary group then the little knowledge can go a long way in making sure that both sides can communicate, progressively learn from each other, and ultimately just do a good job in whatever they might be working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do you get started? In other words, if a clinical researcher is interested in learning more about data analysis do we have to start by proving Bayes theorem? Well, I am of the opinion that the first step is to simply equip a clinical researcher with the bare minimum communication tools to be able to talk with a data science specialist. One of those tools is to have a basic input-output knowledge about different data analysis methods. The basic idea here is that for any given analysis methods the biomedical research should know what is the type of data that should go in, and what type of result it should provide as an output?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for a two-sample t-test, the biomedical researcher should think of the test as having the ability to compare how a continuous variable differs across two samples. For example, how body mass index compares between males and females. This is the input. Then the biomedical researcher should be able to look at a table with results from a t-test and understand the main concepts such as the mean value for each group, the p value and what it represents. That&amp;#39;s the output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sure that at this point there might be people screaming out there by saying that t-tests are so much more complex and an introduction without x, x being a discussion about confidence intervals, or t distribution families, or how robust t-tests are to non-normal variables, or ... But I would argue that while all these points are important, they are not necessary to provide biomedical researchers with information so that they can start talking with data scientists. For example, if the data scientist took the body mass index and then turned it into a categorical variable, the biomedical researcher should be asking why rather than just saying amen. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might come back to this topic later with some more solid examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Theory of constraints, vocation and learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/17/toc_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/17/toc_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LUVTArRvfJs/UjCwxvXLmAI/AAAAAAAA3zQ/p_dQuxAAOS8/w535-h717-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the mother of all knowledge, Wikipedia, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_constraints&quot;&gt;Theory of Constraints (TOC) is defined as&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory of constraints (TOC) is a management paradigm that views any manageable system as being limited in achieving more of its goals by a very small number of constraints. There is always at least one constraint, and TOC uses a focusing process to identify the constraint and restructure the rest of the organization around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look closely, TOC is probably the modern version of vocational tests as a way to guide learning. Reason is that learning is no longer the response to a lifelong vocation, but instead a minute-by-minute, ever changing need in regular daily lives. For example, at this point I might need to learn how to write a short script to scrape a number of pages for my a paper I have to write, while in two hours I will need to learn the best possible way to run a meeting where members tend to be unfocused. None of these skills are captured by vocational tests, and yet these two skills are what I need the most at those very moments since without them I am highly constrained. My paper writing might take forever without scraping, and my meeting will be a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you then think of learning as being determined by TOC, the two problems people putting learning systems in place will face are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem identification&lt;/em&gt;: How do you help people that the problem they have is addressable by a given skill? For example, I might think that writing that paper will indeed take six months, and that my messy meeting is just the way it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skill identification&lt;/em&gt;: How do you help somebody find out that, once they identify a problem, what they need to learn is a specific skill, when in multiple cases they might not even be aware of that skill? For example, most people don&amp;#39;t know what scraping is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem and skill identification are both coaching components, and as we recently learned from &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/16/coaching_learning/&quot;&gt;Tutorspree&amp;#39;s experience&lt;/a&gt;, coaching is difficult to scale. Lots of work ahead of educators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Tutorspree, coaching and scalability</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/16/coaching_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/16/coaching_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-orbuyeobWS4/UjCwzggIHpI/AAAAAAAA3z4/QQl9DkJeHOQ/w535-h717-no/fractal8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindsight is 20/20, and I myself struggled in multiple attempts to scale up coaching programs in academics. And so this all to say that the following post is in no way a criticism of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sfgate.com/technology/businessinsider/article/After-Raising-1-8-Million-Y-Combinator-Startup-4797113.php&quot;&gt;Tutorspree, which has recently shut down&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a long story short, the founders themselves acknowledge that the main problem they faced was scalability, and that&amp;#39;s not surprising. Good quality coaching is such a personal endeavor, requiring a lot of energy from the coach to deeply understand not only the area of the person being coached, but also his/her skills and weaknesses. So, it&amp;#39;s almost like doing it yourself, except that you do not have (and don&amp;#39;t want to have) a great degree of control over what exactly the person being coached will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, does all this means that it is impossible to scale coaching up. I don&amp;#39;t think so, but in order to do it well it likely requires some basic principles if you are attempting to create a coaching environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Niches: coaching is a specialized activity, and so you&amp;#39;ve got to segment your groups. One fits all is hard. For example, it would be difficult to create a single environment to coach programmers and healthcare professionals side by side. They require different content, with content being presented in different formats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide good support content so that coaches&amp;#39; time can be spent on problem and skill needs identification: Coaches are good because they can pinpoint what the likely problem is in a given situation, and then point the person being coached to the skill he will likely need to address that problem. A good environment for coaching therefore needs to provide good content presented in an adequate framework. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good content: Having access to good content will save coaches&amp;#39; time and therefore attract them. Think about it, if I am coaching somebody and then have to explain every single detail on my own, my life would be a living hell. If instead I can focus on identifying problems and then simply pointing the people I coach to good material, my job is significantly simplified. Goes without saying that the coach herself has to be trained to locate this content. Ultimate result here is what I &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/30/whole_task_ladder/&quot;&gt;mentioned in a previous post&lt;/a&gt; as a ladder: If the person can learn the basics from good, automatic content in the form of videos, slides, exercises, etc, then the coaching time will be optimized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good content placed in a variety of learning frameworks: good content resources used by coaches have to be constantly evolving not only in terms of format. For example, a step-by-step learning material might be a great resource at one point, but later on a coach might want to point the person being coached to a learning material that instead talks about the most common errors in a certain field. &amp;quot;Step by step&amp;quot; material and learning by showing common &amp;quot;errors and fixes&amp;quot; are different frameworks to present the same problem, both needed in different situations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communication platforms: In our day and age, it&amp;#39;s unlikely that your dream come true coach will be your next door neightboor. Communication platforms used to be very difficult to find a few years ago, nowadays we have plenty of good options. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/+/learnmore/hangouts/&quot;&gt;Google Hangouts&lt;/a&gt; are my favorite, provided the coach and the person being coached both have access to a decent Internet connection and are reasonably computer literate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coaching mentality: To be a coach you have to think like a coach or, even better, you have to like to be a coach. In other words, you have to think about the other person first. Finding the right person used to be a nightmare, since you had to define psychometric characteristics that were predictive of good coaching and then hope that they would work. They usually wouldn&amp;#39;t. But now there are social networks, which allow people to communicate about who the good and bad coaches might be. So, way less of a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Rawl's Theory of Justice and a simple example in learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/15/theory_justice_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/15/theory_justice_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-IBBXUvOYK_4/UjCwtvLDeMI/AAAAAAAA3yM/ATIOX7v3YoQ/w535-h717-no/%253Bldf.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I propose to teach you differential equations, but you have never taken calculus before. Then I announce that your whole life depends on your final score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s clear that this course will be a massacre at least, very few people would dispute that. But then this is, in a very simplistic way, the very basis of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Theory_of_Justice&quot;&gt;Rawl&amp;#39;s Theory of Justice&lt;/a&gt;. In other words, to assume that any two people will be coming from the exact level when you give them an &amp;quot;equal opportunity&amp;quot; is just insane. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if this is so easy to understand with a simple example, why is it so hard to bring to all other parts of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>What does market research mean when you are talking about an experiential product?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/14/learning_markets/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/14/learning_markets</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-e2dhovtUWJs/UjCEh05PaSI/AAAAAAAA3w8/FWNUmy4hTNA/w480-h680-no/fr.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve written before about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/agile_online_courses/&quot;&gt;use of market research in online learning&lt;/a&gt;, the main gist being that before you invest a ton of time on a course product with some new spin, you should first test the market. In other words, the principle should be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Power-Pull-Smartly-Things-ebook/dp/B0039KO9ZK/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;qid=1378912778&quot;&gt;pull&lt;/a&gt; rather than push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then if your new learning product involves a new type of experience, then it could be hard or next to impossible to convey what that new experience would be in a market research survey. For example, if your course is about to create a new level of personalization and interaction, that experience won&amp;#39;t get through in a short description or even in a well-crafted video. People have to try it so that they might get a better idea on whether they would like to pay for the product and exactly how much they would be willing to pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I am now thinking that market research might be simply the first iterative cycle in an Agile chain. The process then should start with a market research, followed by an immediate release of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product&quot;&gt;minimum viable product (MVP)&lt;/a&gt;. Only then increments to that product are made through a series of small randomized experiments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, market research is not a definitive step, do or die. Instead, market research is just the start of an extensive experiment where the path can be re-oriented dynamically oriented as you go. So, if a given niche wants personalization, then given then the type of personalization they want. If their main need is deep content, then deep content it is, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Tim Ferris and the Agile/Lean movement</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/13/ferris_agile/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/13/ferris_agile</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-rwgJOrePL-o/UiNM5hY0NsI/AAAAAAAA3IA/SQWPHn5COpo/w680-h480-no/fractal5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot has been written about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/4-Hour-Workweek-Expanded-Updated-ebook/dp/B002WE46UW/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;qid=1378911156&quot;&gt;Tim Ferris&amp;#39; book on the four-hour week&lt;/a&gt; concept. Tim is an incredible marketer, and he was right in pitching the title as being able to work four hours a week to make 40k/month and travel around the world. But then, if you look closer there is a much deeper message there, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim&amp;#39;s approach seems to be that there is always an easy way to do things, and that people should go for the low-hanging fruit. Although this is stated in a completely different way, there is a ton of parallels here with the Lean/Agile movement, when they say that you should start with the simplest possible hack or minimum viable product. If it doesn&amp;#39;t work you toss it, if it does work you take it from there in multiple iterating cycles where each cycle delivers a functional but likely ever incomplete product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I think that Tim adds one more essential component to this. If I have an idea and I put this idea inside an Agile cycle, I am basically missing one of the most important steps, which is to search for the perfectly hackable idea. In other words, it&amp;#39;s not really about trying to get a hack out of a certain area, but instead trying to find areas where a hack is likely to turn things around. Searching with a hacking mind then implies discarding a lot of ideas before you even get started. Essentially, you toss out everything that might not seem like is waiting to be easily disrupted. This search, and the focus to keep it simple later on is the real hacking art, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Functions, objects, and experiences in learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/12/functions_objects_experiences/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/12/functions_objects_experiences</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-BLGsGkbyiaA/Ui4lcl3h32I/AAAAAAAA3rA/Tpf0mjyQbRg/w800-h500-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day I was reading somewhere that in the R stats language almost everything is either an object and/or a function (might be the Chambers book, but I am not sure). If you like to think in terms of semantics, this does make sense in that you can create meaning by making an object generate action through a function to create another object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s then tempting to establish an analogy with learning to say that when trying to teach a skill to somebody all you need is to show them how to gather the raw material to put the skill to practice (an object) and then to teach this person to put the skill in action (function), so that an endproduct (a resulting object) can be generated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all sounds perfect, except that when you bring the functions-objects duo to humans you end up mixing a third component: Experience or, like some people prefer to call it, the situations surrounding functions &amp;amp; objects. Situations will affect how humans use functions/actions to act upon objects/things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example: I might coach a novice biomedical researcher by telling her that working in interdisciplinary groups is a good thing. However, if she feels that a given person would not be a good professional match for her, then the decision should be to not establish a collaboration with that individual. Also, I might coach another novice research into always reaching out to peers for further advice. That being said, if that novice researcher does not reach out in a way that is socially acceptable to within that research group, then no help will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Hacking math equations: Math for Big Data practitioners</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/11/equation_hacking/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/11/equation_hacking</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-XQ6g7dMjySo/Uid8d9gbdPI/AAAAAAAA3Y4/MwHG-ah2ngg/w700-h500-no/brown2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is actually an expansion of something I wrote on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/McTvKEVX5UW&quot;&gt;Google Plus&lt;/a&gt; and which is an idea that has been hunting me down for a while. As full disclosure, I am by no means a mathematician, although my PhD was focused on statistics and so I can say I come from a quantitative background. The basic principle is that a number of Big Data practitioners is scared of mathematical proofs, and therefore end up missing the inner guts of algorithms they might be working with. Sure, they have a rough practical understanding of things, but the algorithms are treated more likely a black box, something goes in, magic happens, something comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I will have an opportunity to demonstrate and hopefully hone the method in future posts, the idea here is simply to lay the main steps and principles down. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by breaking an equation down into its functional components. I call this the hacking approach, which is used around the Web in quite a few places. Check for example the outstanding post by Stuart Riffle on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.altdevblogaday.com/2011/05/17/understanding-the-fourier-transform/&quot;&gt;Fourier Transforms&lt;/a&gt;. The more relevant portion of his post is when he color codes different portions of the main equation and then &lt;a href=&quot;http://altdevblogaday.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/DerivedDFT.png&quot;&gt;explains each portion in isolation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you&amp;#39;ve broken the main equation into components, then test each component in isolation using numeric in algorithms. My preference is for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; just because I&amp;#39;m a bit more familiar with it, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://ipython.org/&quot;&gt;iPython&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://julialang.org/&quot;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; or whatever you might be comfortable with will do, including even languages that might handle symbolic computations like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/doc/reference/calculus/sage/calculus/calculus.html&quot;&gt;Sage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally bring all the parts together and continue running experiments to check the equation&amp;#39;s behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it&amp;#39;s no rocket science and it will likely get the data science practioner&amp;#39;s understanding of the underlying math to the next level. A few important additional points in relation to the equation hacking method that I would like to cover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The method is not new, and multiple people have laid down fairly similar things for a long time. Among them Jack Holmer](http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=1815063&amp;amp;authType=NAME&lt;em&gt;SEARCH&amp;amp;authToken=a4P7&amp;amp;locale=en&lt;/em&gt;US&amp;amp;srchid=56292141378682048157&amp;amp;srchindex=1&amp;amp;srchtotal=8&amp;amp;trk=vsrp&lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;res_name&amp;amp;trkInfo=VSRPsearchId%3A56292141378682048157%2CVSRPtargetId%3A1815063%2CVSRPcmpt%3Aprimary) with his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.systemdynamics.org/conferences/1983/proceed/parallel-vol2/homer920.pdf&quot;&gt;partial-model testing&lt;/a&gt; for System Dynamics models, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks/conrad_wolfram_teaching_kids_real_math_with_computers.html&quot;&gt;Conrad Wolfram in his TED talk&lt;/a&gt; focusing on Mathematica, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mosaic-web.org/&quot;&gt;Project Mosaic&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.macalester.edu/%7Ekaplan/&quot;&gt;Daniel Kaplan&lt;/a&gt; and others, and the proponents of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Mathematics-Experiment-2nd-Edition-Plausible/dp/1568814429/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1378739569&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=experimental+mathematics&quot;&gt;experimental mathematics&lt;/a&gt; like Borwein and Bailey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intention is not to replace mathematical proofs, that would be stupid to say the least. That being said, proofs are a mathematicians business, while our business as practitioners is to have the best possible understanding of what we are doing. The goal with the hacking equations method is then to increase the intelligibility by those who, like me, did plenty of proofs in grad school but who don&amp;#39;t have the mathematical sophistication to understand complex math. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This method can&amp;#39;t obviously be followed without some basic math pre-requisites. At this point I would say that the following would certainly help:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some basic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Theory-Logic-Dover-Mathematics-ebook/dp/B00CB2MKPI/ref=sr_1_1?s=digital-text&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1378743111&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=set+theory&quot;&gt;Set Theory&lt;/a&gt; to understand the notation &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/How-Solve-Mathematical-Princeton-ebook/dp/B0073X0IOA/ref=tmm_kin_title_0&quot;&gt;Proof principles&lt;/a&gt;  since even if you are not going to do the proofs by hand, some general principles will help you understand how to prove something using a computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/math/calculus&quot;&gt;Calculus&lt;/a&gt; there are some attempts now by the Project Mosaic to &lt;a href=&quot;http://test.causeweb.org/wiki/mosaic/index.php/Pub114&quot;&gt;teach Calculus using R&lt;/a&gt; but I haven&amp;#39;t tried it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Hands-On-Matrix-Algebra-Using-Applications/dp/9814313696&quot;&gt;Linear algebra&lt;/a&gt;, and Vinod&amp;#39;s book is extraordinary, just too bad that it doesn&amp;#39;t have a Kindle version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Solving-Differential-Equations-Use-ebook/dp/B00DGERDI4/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;sr=&amp;amp;qid=&quot;&gt;Differential equations&lt;/a&gt;, and here Soetaert&amp;#39;s book is definitely the place to go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>T skills in learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/10/t_nuggets/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/10/t_nuggets</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-BRpTBRSQTq8/UieF5TsNFwI/AAAAAAAA3bQ/FUZPcsHQDXM/s558-no/fractal5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- need to clarify the nugget portion --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have been thinking a lot recently about an absolutely brilliant &lt;a href=&quot;http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2013/8/166303-teaching-programming-the-way-it-works-outside-the-classroom/fulltext&quot;&gt;post by Philip Guo&lt;/a&gt; on how programming is done in the real world, and therefore how it should probably be taught. The whole concept can be summarized by the sequence forage, tinker, weld, grow, doubt, and refactor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people would call the essence of a hack, but notice that I am using the word hack here is one of the highest possible levels of a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this post so much that I think the whole concept can be further expanded to cover the connection between programming and any area outside of programming. This means once you reached the stage when you are done tweaking the code your foraged, you could potentially bring in pieces of non-programming methods. Here is an example: let&amp;#39;s say that I decided to run some Big Data experiments using a method called &lt;a href=&quot;http://lsa.colorado.edu/papers/dp1.LSAintro.pdf&quot;&gt;latent semantic analysis (LSA)&lt;/a&gt;. Blatantly oversimplifying things, LSA will extract concepts within free text that are highly associated and infer that they are all pointing to a higher construct. For example, if the concepts of grades, intelligence, diligence, and persistence keep clustering across units of text, I might infer that these concepts probably have something in common from the perspective of the writer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, following the forage-refactor sequence from Philip, I would grab a piece of LSA code, play with it a bit, insert my own data and make it work, and then could maybe bring in a chunk of graphical source code to illustrate my brand new LSA analysis. This is all good, but instead of bringing in another piece of code, I could also blend my initial analysis with some qualitative research, meaning to conduct an interview with the writer and see whether my analysis does make sense. The difference between inserting yet another chunk of code and introducing a qualitative methodology is subtle but, I think, important. It means that one of the essential components of novelty is to blend skills that are usually distant. In my example, almost every data scientist who knows LSA likely knows how to graphically display data, but a far smaller number of them are intimately connected to qualitative research. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some clarification is probably in order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To say that a skill is distant from each other, I explicitly mean that the people with one set of skills communicate very little with the people who know the other skill set. So, distant is used here in the social network analysis context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to get this kind of blending a T skill set will be required. I honestly don&amp;#39;t know who came up with the T metaphor, but to me it summarizes the essence of what is needed in this kind of situation. The &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; skill has a long vertical arm of expertise in one area, and a shorter horizontal, cross-disciplinary range of skills across areas. Call it the 21st century version of our beloved polymath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The central point of the T skill is the crossing point between the vertical and the horizontal arms, or how to make the two lead into something potentially useful, but that is another whole story that I will likely come back to in future posts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Just-in-time learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/09/jit_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/09/jit_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-1PR_O2WTanE/UimrLWkFkxI/AAAAAAAA3e4/1bz2HwoEUwg/s558-no/Mandelbrot+view.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People attempting to predict what the future of learning might be is obviously fooling themselves: The variety of styles will likely be as large as it gets, fades will come and go, blending among themselves in what promises to be an awesome ecology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, at the risk of making a fool of myself, or maybe actually trying to make a fool of myself, here is my own prediction: One of the important components in future education will be just in time (JIT) learning, to the point of the very expression JIT becoming synonymous with learning. Rather than trying to define it, here is a vision: I am doing a task for personal or work-related reasons  and in order to complete that task I need to have a certain ability and access some materials, but I don&amp;#39;t know how to do it, where to get the required stuff, and who to ask. I search for the closest possible skill course, decide that it is close enough to my needs, and decide on whether I want to buy the learning nugget or get the freely available ones. Once I grab the learning nugget, it will first show me how to quickly run their example from start to finish and then how to adapt that same working example to my particular case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a bunch of detail hidden into this description, and so let&amp;#39;s dissect some of its pieces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am talking about a task that could be for work or personal reasons, but the distinction between the two is getting more and more blurred everyday. If you hope to retire for any reason other than inability to do absolutely anything, think twice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By a task here I mean things such as programming a computer, building a bacteria to create something you want, building a certain 3D model for printing, communicating with another person ... anything requiring a skill set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Searching for the right learning material will likely be a mix of search and social activity, similar to what it already is but more efficient, perhaps semantic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will be possible to understand, at a glance, exactly what kind of skill set you will have at the end of that learning experience. This means that practical outcomes will be more important than the whole theory that comes along with the learning is experience, theory will come later when and if needed. Again, this is JIT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to deliver content that is precisely what people need, a great deal of dynamic, real-time market research will be going on, with an even better experience monitoring after the content is delivered. The continuous production of additional content will be driven by both the market research and the experience monitoring. In other words, markets will be highly segmented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, like any prediction writer, I will likely regret having written this one, but it&amp;#39;s written anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>