<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	
	<title type="text" xml:lang="en"></title>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" href="http://rpietro.github.io/feed/" rel="self"/>
 	<link type="text" href="hhttp://rpietro.github.io/" rel="alternate"/>
	<updated>2013-08-31T23:16:30-04:00</updated>
	<id>http://http://rpietro.github.io/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Ricardo Pietrobon</name>
	</author>
	<rights>Copyright (c) 2013, Ricardo Pietrobon; all rights reserved.</rights>
	
	
	<entry>
		<title>Basic skills for clinical researchers working with biomedical data</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/31/basic_skills_clinical_researchers/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/31/basic_skills_clinical_researchers</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-Gp5-KazjVkM/UiJv_vHpL6I/AAAAAAAA3G0/5O9f_B2Osw4/w500-h300-no/blog.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a simple list of skills that, in my personal opinion, make it for a good set of skills a clinical researcher should have in order to explore a topic from multiple design perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cross-sectional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RCTs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qualitative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surveys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longitudinal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time to event&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Methods and standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Results and mock tables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analysis interpretation

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inferential tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time to event&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SEM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;qualitative and qca&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data management and exploratory graphical analysis

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data cleaning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Association plots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qualitative data collection

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data collection, interview techniques, storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Survey data collection

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;questionnaire set up, mturkR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding existing data

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repositories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;csv&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what is xml, json, rdf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;large data and mysql&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what is hadoop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing of grant proposals

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specific aims, significance, innovation, approach, cvs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature search 

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;google search, pubmed, reference manager, map against manuscript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproducible research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project management

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;agile, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissemination 

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blogging and white papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;presentation - audience, fear, handling difficult questions, presentation structure, videos &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Complex Learning IDM, whole tasks, and task ladders</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/30/whole_task_ladder/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/30/whole_task_ladder</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.edudemic.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/boy-writing-with-pencil.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I truly admire &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Steps-Complex-Learning-Four-Component-ebook/dp/B009WMBP7O/ref=tmm_kin_title_0&quot;&gt;Merrienboer&amp;#39;s Complex Learning instructional design model (IDM)&lt;/a&gt;, every time a fixed set of guidelines is defined, it almost automatically sets itself for exceptions. Complex Learning follows the rule, and here I will try to present a problem that I believe is an exception to one of the central tenets behind Complex Learning: The need to use Whole Tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merrienboer sees whole tasks as being authentic and representative of what students are going to find in their daily personal or professional practice. In &lt;a href=&quot;http://dspace.ou.nl/bitstream/1820/2327/1/Ten%20Steps%20to%20Complex%20Learning%20-%20Sage%2021st%20Century.pdf&quot;&gt;his words&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;text language-text&quot; data-lang=&quot;text&quot;&gt;These approaches all focus on authentic learning tasks as the driving force for teaching and learning because such tasks are instrumental in helping learners to integrate knowledge, skills, and atti- tudes (often referred to as competences), stimulate the coordination of skills constituent to solving problems or carrying out tasks, and facilitate the transfer of what has been learned to new and often unique tasks and problem situations (Merrill, 2002b; van Merriënboer, 2007; van Merriënboer &amp;amp; Kirschner, 2001).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In situations where a whole task cannot be brought in as a component of the educational plan, then Merrienboer recommends that it be substituted by segments that retain the whole task spirit, which completely makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, the idea of relying on whole tasks as a rule violates what happens with most experts as they climb up the learning ladder. For example, if you have a lab director or store manager with a number of assistants, at one point this person will no longer need or even want to execute tasks from start to finish in order to move up in their expertise. Instead, they will rely on their assistants to execute the tasks that they are already familiar with, waiting for them to filter the more complex problems that are then brought to their attention. In this ladder mechanism individuals rely on others to do the tasks they already know by heart, waiting for them to bring more sophisticated problems to their attention, ultimately sharpening their skills without unnecessary repetition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I have not approached Merrienboer himself regarding this problem, and maybe his response would be that the definition of what constitutes a whole tasks would get narrower and narrower as expertise is built. In any case, this is perhaps more of an addition to his impressive IDM rather than a flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Learning Agile project management applied to clinical research</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/29/agile_management/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/29/agile_management</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://tiny-giant-books.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/agile-edge-case-ninja.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Agile mania&lt;/em&gt; started within &lt;a href=&quot;http://agilemanifesto.org/&quot;&gt;software development&lt;/a&gt;, but has been gradually moving into business areas, the most famous being the whole &lt;a href=&quot;http://theleanstartup.com/&quot;&gt;Lean Startup movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, some areas such as biomedical research are fairly slow to adopt, usually under untested claims that &lt;em&gt;this is not for us&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;won&amp;#39;t work here&lt;/em&gt;. Sure enough, full-blown Agile is not for everybody or every project, but that doesn&amp;#39;t excuse people from at least looking at which features of this methodology could potentially bring value. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what are the main principles behind Agile and how exactly could they fit to the whole clinical research enterprise? Below is a non-comprehensive first shot at both of these questions selecting the ones I personally think are most relevant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Focus on your client&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start a clinical research project, you have to have a clear picture of the goal you are trying to achieve and who is interested in the final product. Clinical research could accommodate multiple goals, but I would probably argue that the following are among the top ones: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create knowledge that is brand new, filling a gap in the literature. Your client here will be your journal editor and your peers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create knowledge that will be useful to patients, addressing a need that wasn&amp;#39;t fulfilled up to this point. Your primary client here are patients around the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do something that is achievable within the resources at your disposal. Your main client here are the people working with you, as you don&amp;#39;t want them to embark on a project unless you know it can get to a successful closure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although all of this might sound like common sense, most clinical research project will miss one or more of these: Starting a project without thoroughly evaluating how novel the project is, focusing on something that is new but trivial, or embarking on a project that is clearly impossible to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Incomplete and functioning products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile assumes that the world is not only constantly changing, but that you are also constantly learning about the world around you. As a function of both of these principles, Agile says that you should not embark on long development periods without exposing something that is both incomplete and functioning to your client. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing this to clinical research, one of the applications is that you should not design a full blown clinical study without doing a quick and dirty test of each one of its phases. For example, I have seen researchers designing studies where they honestly thought that a single patient would answer a questionnaire with 100 pages. The worst part is that I am not kidding. This assumption of participants with super powers and infinite time and patience went untested throughout the funding acquisition, staff recruitment, ethical approval, just to fail miserably when the first research participant came through. This could have been easily avoided with a simple test at the very beginning. Again, it doesn&amp;#39;t have to be complete, a simple portion of the protocol will do. But it has to be functional, meaning that it has to reproduce at least some aspects of the protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Iterate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iteration is a function of incomplete and functional products. In other words, you keep running small trials, having it evaluated by your client, and then improving a bit every time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our impossible 100-page data collection study, a quick test would show that 100-pages is impossible, a second test would show that even 10 pages is too much, and the final test would show that a very well selected one-page is probably what you need. You then run this through some peers to see whether the final article coming out of that one very well crafted page would provide the answer to your gap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Minimum viable product&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a minimum viable product or MVP is that because you work in cycles, you don&amp;#39;t want your first product to be perfect. Actually, perfection is probably not in your dictionary. Instead, what you want is something that is progressively better, achievable, but at the same time adapted to your environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the clinical research world, you don&amp;#39;t want to design the study that will provide answers to everything, from the cure of cancer all the way to the end of the Syria conflict. Instead, you want something that will answer your question in the simplest possible way. Once that is achieved, then you can increment your study with an additional cohort or a longer follow-up, or whatever you think might bring value to the study in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Trello&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people love &lt;a href=&quot;https://trello.com/&quot;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt; since it&amp;#39;s not only an outstanding software but also free of charge. Although the details of how to use it in an Agile environment are beyond what I plan on covering in this post, there are plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.civicactions.com/blog/2012/oct/10/five_tips_for_using_trello_for_scrum&quot;&gt;online tutorials&lt;/a&gt; on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the beginning, none of these principles are all or nothing. You can use bits and pieces of each of them or go full force. The point here is that you should not be religious about Agile, but you should instead know about each of the principles and then choose which ones are the best for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;can be adapted, how much is used is completely open&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Enriched and personalized learning content</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/27/enriched_content/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/27/enriched_content</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gegeblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/protein-food.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main problems with online learning is that, no matter what we might do, so far it will necessarily lag behind a personal coach. Take for example the outstanding learning framework just posted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/XRQxPEhLuia&quot;&gt;Khan Academy group&lt;/a&gt;. This framework is right on the spot, as it walks students through a real scenario, talks about everything that is important from the perspective of an expert, ultimately attempting to make the student think like an expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, it&amp;#39;s perfect, except for one crucial thing: It&amp;#39;s not personalized to what the student needs at that very moment. In other words, when students say that they want to learn how to program, few if any would choose to learn how to program in general rather than creating a very specific program that would meet a very specific need they might have. In the end, what they are looking for is not to become programmers, but instead to learn how to program a certain thing to a achieve a specific objective. A personal coach could walk them through this process, a current online program cannot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then what are the options? Creating an infinite number of tutorials is clearly not one of them, but perhaps a combination of the following factors could help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Focus on a niche&lt;/em&gt;: From a marketing perspective, focus on a narrow niche that might make sense from an ROI perspective, and then go global. Going global will expand the number of people potentially taking the course even if the number of people interested is small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Modularize the course structure&lt;/em&gt;: In psychometrics there is a field called &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/Zf2oedoqm7g&quot;&gt;Automatic Item Generation&lt;/a&gt; where items or questions are built as models, and then variations are introduced inside the models to generate a huge number of items. For example, if one wants to teach how to make a diagnosis of a set of abdominal conditions, it would be possible to list a group of symptoms, signs, and lab exams, and then associate each of the combinations with certain diagnoses and therapeutic plans. The same could potentially be applicable to different types of education. The key here would be to constantly feed these exercises through a group of motivated content creators and curators. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ladder mechanism&lt;/em&gt;: Establish a ladder mechanism where the initial, more general part of learning is done through more general material. Then, once students have a general basis, then and only then they start with more individualized type or coaching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation integrated into daily activities&lt;/em&gt;: here the main concept is that as our ability to document our daily activities increases as a function of automation through software, more and more material will be available to students regarding what might be the current practice of a given professional. For example, if a given physician has a specially effective way of treating patients, and if this workflow is carefully followed through a series of software applications, then a student would be able to learn about that workflow by looking at the documentation trail left from that physician. This last path will obviously involve the 

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to track information, like an electronic medical record tracking every single step of the physician&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the concurrent documentation by the professional to enhance the data, or the physician constantly making notes to clarify any practice that might not be appropriately captured by the electronic medical record&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the existence of tools that will facilitate the transformation of that data into useful information, such as graphical tools that might make the workflow clear enough&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>3D models in healthcare education - bone fractures</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/26/3D_anatomy_healthcare_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/26/3D_anatomy_healthcare_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://openi.nlm.nih.gov/imgs/rescaled512/116429_1471-2474-3-14-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now testing the use of 3D models to educate healthcare professionals in relation to the diagnosis, biomechanics, and treatment of bone fractures. Starting with wrist fracture models created in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.autodesk.com/products/autodesk-maya/overview&quot;&gt;Maya&lt;/a&gt; since they are so common, we decided to focus on 3D models for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Detail&lt;/em&gt;: Although the use of radiographs and other imaging modalities are certainly essential in training healthcare professionals to diagnose them, 3D models can show details that might not be possible with a regular clinical image. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rare cases&lt;/em&gt;: Some fracture types are just not common enough to be easy to find at imaging repositories. In contrast, it takes a few minutes to create a highly quality fracture model that can be sliced, diced and rendered in any way the instructor might want, including giving the model an aspect that looks like an radiograph. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biomechanics&lt;/em&gt;: Here I don&amp;#39;t mean the fracture mechanism, which is usually what an orthopedic surgeon will think about when the word biomechanics comes up. Although mechanism could easily be reproduced in a dynamic model, an arguably more important aspect is how muscles, ligaments, gravity and other mechanical factors contribute to make fracture fragments displace in one way or another. The idea here is that students will learn why the fracture behaves the way it does, with obvious implications for how it should be treated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Treatment&lt;/em&gt;: Although treatment is not only about biomechanics, biomechanics does play an important role in defining how a certain fracture type should be treated. The idea for treatment then is to build dynamic models that will show how a given device or immobilization method interacts with the fracture biomechanics, making the treatment process more rational rather than an act of memorization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we are focusing only on static images, but dynamic ones should be coming up soon, along with evidence-based information. One of my surprises when going over musculoskeletal models available in the most common 3D repositories is how poor they are. They will frequently lack very important bone details, have details that absolutely do not exist, the relationship among the bones is just plain wrong, among many other things. If the situation with skeletons is overall poor, it gets much worse when it comes to models combining bones, ligaments, cartilage, muscles and other anatomical structures. Let&amp;#39;s then not even talk about dynamic models. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, a ton of work moving forward. &lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Educating innovators: a blogged book</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/25/blog_book/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/25/blog_book</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-uvnOeJVVnSc/Ug0mEyVLwjI/AAAAAAAA0-E/X06aV67g4TQ/w506-h512/Screen+Shot+2013-08-15+at+4.02.57+PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just finished reading Nina Amir&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/How-Blog-Book-Publish-ebook/dp/B0084IUD9S/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;sr=&amp;amp;qid=&quot;&gt;How to blog a book&lt;/a&gt;. All in all it seems like an interesting, sound concept. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although one would possibly question whether somebody would feel &lt;em&gt;cheated&lt;/em&gt; in buying a book when parts of it are online, there is something about the book as a unit that is hard to describe. I noticed this when I started consulting &lt;a href=&quot;http://adv-r.had.co.nz/&quot;&gt;Hadley Wickham&amp;#39;s book on R Advanced Programming&lt;/a&gt;. I have probably read some of his chapters at least four times, and yet I can barely wait for the ebook to come out. Why? Perhaps it&amp;#39;s because it will have a final touch to it, sections will be more connected than they are now. Looking back, these are probably not reasons that would justify the buying of a book, maybe I&amp;#39;m just trying to rationalize the need to say thanks for putting together such a fantastic resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, whether I will be blogging a book once again? Probably not for a while, but never say never ...&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Scaffolding education: The ability to search, understand key concepts and play with field-specific tools</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/15/triad/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/15/triad</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.emints.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Scaffolding_Berlin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Merrienboer&amp;#39;s central concepts in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Steps-Complex-Learning-Four-Component-ebook/dp/B009WMBP7O/ref=sr_1_1_title_1_kin?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1376578242&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Complex Design Instructional Design Model&lt;/a&gt; is that as students learn, they should be progressively stripped from &amp;quot;spoon-fed education.&amp;quot; In other words, when you start learning you need to be observed and assisted in every action, but as you progress then this support has to be substituted for a learning on how to learn. Merrienboer calls this a &lt;em&gt;scaffolding process&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I our day and age, I believe that one of the central characteristics of this scaffolding process is the ability to search online. But while most people think that searching is something done for the purposes of gathering information about a topic, searching alone is only part of the full-story. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, concepts are only useful if they are put to a purpose, such as extending them by being able to consult more complex, deeper sources of information. In addition, concepts will play a central role in actually discussing with experts in the field to be able to obtain feedback the use of those concepts. This feedback will turn concepts that were originally static into something dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, searching will provide students with sources of tools where these concepts can be put into practice. For example, if a student is attempting to learn what a statistical average is, simply learning the concept is not enough. The student has to try the concept using whatever tool on a dataset. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of concepts and tools is not mine, but was instead developed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fas.harvard.edu/%7Ehsdept/bios/galison.html&quot;&gt;Peter Gallison&lt;/a&gt; in what he called &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trading_zones&quot;&gt;trading zones&lt;/a&gt;. Tool use and using concepts in an interactive way can also be interpreted as an instance of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situated_cognition&quot;&gt;situated cognition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The university's dilemma</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/12/university_dilemma/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/12/university_dilemma</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://static.guim.co.uk/sys-images/Guardian/Pix/pictures/2012/7/9/1341835095092/The-number-of-university--008.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The university is one of the most interesting institutions in our society, and yet it currently faces one of the biggest dilemmas of its entire existence. Founded under the premise that the best minds would have the time to freely think about all aspects of science and society, the university now faces a major dilemma that can be described in the following terms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it simply decides to keep its ivory tower status, it becomes out of the business chain while producing knowledge that is irrelevant for anybody other than its peers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it tries to align with national and international funding agencies, it turns professors into professional grant writers whose life is the art of attempting to be aligned with whatever agency might be willing to give them money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it goes the industry funding way, it becomes a pet. Despite the best intentions by conflict of interest committees researchers will design studies to prove industry products effective and later will hold back any criticism to their products since that would cut their chances of getting the next funding cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it mean that good science can&amp;#39;t be done? Absolutely not, there is still plenty of exciting projects, probably more than ever. But then, the problem persists without a solution that could take the university to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Big Data in Educational Psychometrics</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/11/big_data_educational_psychometrics/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/11/big_data_educational_psychometrics</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.dracutforum.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/check_box_recruiting-300x299.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked all over for a list of international databases containing fields on specific items (questions) from students of any age, focusing on any kind of educational assessment. Given the large number of psychometricians around the world, I was surprised to not find anything so far. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solution was to create a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_international_databases_on_individual_student_achievement_tests&quot;&gt;list on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, which is now organically growing over the past few weeks. If you have any other sources or know of people who would, by all means feel free to add it yourself or add comment in the source code and I will add it for you. The goal here is to make it easier for researchers and students to quickly find data sets that might be used for research papers, item banks, educational policy evaluation, among many other purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Scientific Writing Ninja</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/sci_wri_ninja/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/sci_wri_ninja</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/72/Hokusai-sketches---hokusai-manga-vol6-crop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time our group has been using content models to coach novice biomedical researchers on how to write scientific papers. Results are really good, since it quickly becomes clear to them what the underlying rhetorical structure is behind a paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, so far we have been using static templates, which is a fancy way to say that we simply put together a text with examples on how to write certain sections of a paper on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google doc&lt;/a&gt;. Novice researchers then grab that template and apply it to their own manuscripts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, I have been exposed to a group of international novice researchers focusing on data sciences, which then gives me the flexibility to use some &lt;em&gt;geek tools&lt;/em&gt; that I wouldn&amp;#39;t dare using before. So, although in all honesty this is an ever changing framework and some portions have only been partially tested, here is what the current workflow looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All article writing happens using R markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Editor is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sublimetext.com/&quot;&gt;Sublime Text&lt;/a&gt;, using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wch/SendText&quot;&gt;sendtext&lt;/a&gt; plugin to run code as the text is written. You might want to check &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zoCFjpXa_UY&quot;&gt;this brief tutorial&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protocols are entirely reproducible, including versioning the manuscript itself on &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; through &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;References are inserted through &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&quot;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt;, which is brilliantly connected to the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;cito ontology&lt;/a&gt;. Searches are without a plugin and performed through the browser using specific databases such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed&quot;&gt;PubMed&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/&quot;&gt;JSTOR&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scielo.org&quot;&gt;Scielo&lt;/a&gt;, and the like. Citation analyses are conducted through Google Scholar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Content-Everywhere-Structure-Future-Ready-ebook/dp/B00AEYPLPQ/ref=sr_1_1_bnp_1_kin?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1376085529&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=content+everywhere&quot;&gt;Content models&lt;/a&gt;, or the text being reused across manuscripts, is stored on gists and then pulled into Sublime through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kemayo/sublime-text-2-git/wiki&quot;&gt;gist plugin&lt;/a&gt;. Now, truth being told, using [Sublime snippets] would allow us to make the text substitution much easier, faster and they could also be stored on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, but the ability to store individual gists allows for some perks in relation to the taxonomy (see next item).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taxonomy for the gists involves a first word that determines the overall location within an article (abstract-introduction-methods-results-discussion), followed by the design, and then the specifics of the text chunk itself. For example, a section containing the randomization section within a randomized trial in the methods section could be called something like methods&lt;em&gt;rct&lt;/em&gt;randomization. The chunks are hierarchical, meaning that if I only look for a chunk called methods_rct I would get a gist with the names of all possible text chunks inside the methods section of randomized controlled trial. These sections obviously follow international standards, in the case of the randomized trial the standard being the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.consort-statement.org/&quot;&gt;CONSORT statement&lt;/a&gt;, and the fact that Sublime Text uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://tutsplus.com/lesson/multiple-cursors-and-incremental-search/&quot;&gt;incremental or fuzzy search&lt;/a&gt; makes finding them really easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this system is all but perfect, the main flaws being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because these are gists it is hard for people to make contributions or fork a large number of them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the chunks are still fairly rough. Just to take the CONSORT example, there are currently multiple available versions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the taxonomy has to be better than what it currently is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pondering about creating a course on this and then making the system evolve to a serious library with a consistent taxonomy/ontology and later a plugin that would manage some of these problems. But let&amp;#39;s see. So far I only got the course name down: &lt;em&gt;Scientific Writing Ninja&lt;/em&gt; LOL&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Big learning data that matters: Bringing the excluded back in</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/learning_bigdata/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/learning_bigdata</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://edudemic.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/learningstyles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently read an excellent post from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knewton.com/&quot;&gt;Knewton&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knewton.com/blog/knewton/from-jose/2013/07/18/big-data-in-education/?utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=July+newsletter+New&amp;amp;utm_content=July+newsletter+New+CID_1e4db5006f527cdc859264e27cfc7e06&amp;amp;utm_source=Knewton+Newsletter&amp;amp;utm_term=Read+more#more&quot;&gt;five different types of Big Data in Education &lt;em&gt;that matter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Very briefly, the five types are classified as identity data, user interaction data, inferred content data, system-wide data, inferred student data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I certainly agree that these types do matter, one of the possible interpretations might be that other types might &lt;em&gt;not matter&lt;/em&gt;. Although I am sure that this was not the intention of that post, mine is to come rescue the guys who were left out. 
The list is huge, and my goal here is not to cover them all. So, here is a first shot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before learning happens

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What does the market wants people to know?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What do people themselves want to learn?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Within the learning process

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How immersed are the students by the learning experience?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much do students like the learning experience?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did it the learning experience allow them to keep learning after the course?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Were the students able to put the learning content to practice beyond simply absorbing information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After learning

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How useful was the learning? Did students get a job? Did they get a promotion? Did it lead the student to do social good?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess my point is that big learning data is certainly about the act of absorbing information, but what comes before and after as well as all the other factors that come along also do matter.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Delegation and team formation for researchers</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/delegation_researchers/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/10/delegation_researchers</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.toddmckeever.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/delegation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go over most books on delegation, they will tell you that in order to delegate you have to make sure that the person you are delegating to has to have at least three main characteristics: Has to be willing, has to have the time, and has to have the ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all nice in theory, but in practice the problem is that when you start working with somebody you will usually not know whether this person has these characteristics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s the solution then? One possibility is to follow an &lt;a href=&quot;http://agilemanifesto.org/&quot;&gt;Agile&lt;/a&gt; approach, where tasks are given to somebody in small chunks, and then followed up in an iterative manner. For example, if the task is to do the data management, give the person a tiny chunk of data to be cleaned and then follow-up. If the three criteria were met for that task, then scale up and check. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other aspect of delegation that is often not mentioned, is that delegation is not about passing tasks to others but instead it is one of the first steps in creating a research team. In other words, if the person can complete a task and keeps moving up in terms of difficulty, then this is a dependable member of your team.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>An online course that people would really like to take</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/ideal_course/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/ideal_course</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/3b/Alexander_and_Aristotle.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I enrolled into an online course related to data analysis that I was really looking forward to taking. The instructor was the primary person in the field, I had read his whole book once and a few chapters multiple times. What an opportunity then to be able to ask questions and get answers from the guy himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then the course started. And the course was a reference to the book along with a pdf with some really simplistic questions, and a board controlled by a really well-intended teaching assistant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I was disappointed and ended up dropping the course after a couple days. But then this experience got me thinking about what is it that I would like to see in a large online course, large here meaning a place where the instructor cannot spend time with individual students, but instead has to create an environments where all of them can be managed as a group. Here are some thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would like to work on something that is similar to the task I am trying to accomplish. So, if it&amp;#39;s a certain type of data analysis, I would like to do it from a to z. This also means that I don&amp;#39;t want the task to be broken down into small pieces to only at the end find out how all the parts come together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would like to have tips on where to search for information that might not be provided in the course static info and social&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would like to learn about new tools and also where I could find additional tool. The latter would ideally include static sources of information such as traditional journals or lists as well as social sources where I can interact and ask questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I would like to learn from personal stories talking about their experience with what works and what not, biggest mistakes, early signs of success and whatever they would share while having a beer with me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i would like the course to adapt to me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i would like to make choices in relation to course path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Static sites and reproducible research blogging</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/blog_archeology/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/blog_archeology</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://hq.scisdragons.net/xkruger/files/2011/08/Archeology.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others have mentioned before some of the advantages of static sites like &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, and among them is the use of versioning systems like &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/book&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; on github](https://github.com/). But another hidden advantage is that anybody digging through the directory structure of the site can check which posts might be coming up, and once they are posted how exactly they evolved over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rpietro/rpietro.github.io/tree/master/_drafts&quot;&gt;drafts directory&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rpietro/rpietro.github.io/blob/master/_drafts/2013-07-29-blog_archeology.markdown&quot;&gt;how this specific post evolved&lt;/a&gt; before it got to be published on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then you might be like &lt;em&gt;who cares?&lt;/em&gt; Well, if you&amp;#39;re writing a non-scientific blog post then probably there is less reason to care about the archeology of a certain post. But imagine that the post is instead focused on exploring a given data set for the adverse effects of a certain drug. Well, all of a sudden how exactly the post got to the conclusions it got does matter. For example, did you go in a certain direction that showed no problems just to fish into a little corner that would make your blog post shine? Did multiple people actually contribute to the post? Who did what? All of this would be easy to find if the blog has an underlying versioning system.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>What does Agile mean in terms of online learning?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/agile_online_courses/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/08/agile_online_courses</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.mindjet.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/Agile-Marketing-Series-What-is-Agile-Marketing.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile still is the hype thing to be. Whether it goes by kanban, lean, or whatever other name, the central concepts are more or less the same: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on whoever will use what you are building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in short iterative cycles, delivering something that is incomplete but functioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then does this concept have any connection with the creation of online courses? I think it does at multiple levels. Below are just some possible examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a quick and dirt market research survey before you launch something. In other words, which people care about what you have to say. Once you find a niche, create a course specifically for them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t overdo it, create the simplest possible course you can in the beginning, and then improve from there&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure and experiment, which translates into metrics such as: are people completing the course, do they talk about it and what do they say, if you have some kind of satisfaction metric in there (5 stars will do), what is it that they are saying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>The evolving definition of literacy</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/03/literacy/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/03/literacy</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs-images.forbes.com/marketshare/files/2011/08/abc_blocks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of what constitutes being literate has been changing over time, and the rate of change is accelerating. Until not a long time ago being literate meant the ability to read and write in your own language. But unless your language is English, this definition is really getting outdated, and very soon Chinese is likely going to be joining the English. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then it is not just about reading words, the definition is moving far beyond that. Right now literacy means the ability to be able to skillfully search for information, interpret and possibly analyze data, and write computer programs. Of course it&amp;#39;s not going to stop there, at some point the basic literacy will be to understand and maybe hack biotechnology and maybe neurobiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then again, this is just my opinion ...&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Expert education</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/02/expert_education/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/02/expert_education</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://fabiusmaximus.files.wordpress.com/2013/06/20130621-expert-monkey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard a number of times that experts do not need structured learning environments, all they need is freedom to explore. While I certainly agree with the freedom bit, I think that the portion on not needing structured learning environments is plain wrong. Here is why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;An expert has a focus in one area, but to innovate experts will often, if not always, have to go outside of their domains of expertise. At the boundaries with another discipline every expert becomes a novice. This is what Gallison calls a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trading_zones&quot;&gt;trading zone&lt;/a&gt;, or a place of exchange with people from other fields. I would call this horizontal expansion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within their field of expertise, experts need to be fed with problems at the edge of their current level of expertise so that they can be expanding their expertise to a deeper and deeper level. The problem is that a sophisticated structure is required in order to get to these highly refined problems that are at a level that can push the experts skills to the next level. These are called &amp;quot;ladder environments,&amp;quot; a term I learned from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/profile/view?id=121305572&amp;amp;authType=NAME_SEARCH&amp;amp;authToken=m86Y&amp;amp;locale=en_US&amp;amp;srchid=56292141375494439812&amp;amp;srchindex=1&amp;amp;srchtotal=12&amp;amp;trk=vsrp_people_res_name&amp;amp;trkInfo=VSRPsearchId%3A56292141375494439812%2CVSRPtargetId%3A121305572%2CVSRPcmpt%3Aprimary&quot;&gt;Bob Eberlein&lt;/a&gt; called it a ladder since there is a group of novices or mid-level experts working with a wide range of projects while solving the easier problems and only taking to the expert the most complicated cases. I would call this vertical expansion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, the statement that experts do not require a structured learning environment is an urban legend, but they do require a *different type of environment.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Merrienboering a topic</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/01/merrienboering/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/01/merrienboering</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img1.imagesbn.com/p/9780415807968_p0_v1_s600.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I am coining a new verb, assuming others haven&amp;#39;t done it before me. The 
verb is &lt;em&gt;merrienboering&lt;/em&gt;, or the ability to turn a topic into Merrienboer&amp;#39;s Instructional Design Model called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Steps-Complex-Learning-Four-Component-ebook/dp/B009WMBP7O/ref=tmm_kin_title_0?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1375382850&amp;amp;sr=8-3&quot;&gt;Complex Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will likely post at some point about my understanding of the main components behind Merrienboer&amp;#39;s model, but one of the most attractive features to me is that you start the learning process by getting a complete or whole task completed. That&amp;#39;s right, no more learning one piece at a time to only then putting it all together at the very end. A &lt;em&gt;life is short, eat dessert first&lt;/em&gt; sort of attitude, which I personally connect with the hacker/agile/lean culture. In other words, hack your way into the simplest possible solution, and only start making it fancier.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Mastering an experimental approach to mathematics: Are the expert skills similar to the ones displayed by experts trained in a traditional way?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/01/experimental_math/"/>
		<updated>2013-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/01/experimental_math</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://emis.matem.unam.mx/journals/EM/img/CassiniQuartic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came one more time across a post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/3PGuie75xmx&quot;&gt;what is it like to understand advanced mathematics?&lt;/a&gt;. Although the number of people reaching the level of mastery described in this post are certain few, I wonder what would be the differences in the type of expertise and insight that would be developed when comparing traditional mathematicians vs. those trained primarily from an experimental perspective. I am actually not sure whether there are people who are solely trained as experimental mathematicians, but even a comparison with the ones primarily focusing on experimental mathematics would be fairly interesting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reason for my interest in this topic is that I identify this as the geek/Agile/constructivist/Merrienboer way of doing mathematics, something that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carma.newcastle.edu.au/jon/&quot;&gt;Jonathan Borwein&lt;/a&gt; has been advocating for a while through several books, including his latest &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Modern-Mathematical-Computing-ebook/dp/B00A7QHJR4/ref=tmm_kin_title_0?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1375387549&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;An Introduction to Modern Mathematical Computing: With Mathematica&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps making the book focused on, say, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sagemath.org/&quot;&gt;Sage&lt;/a&gt; would make it more widely accessible, but regardless this is a very exciting field for mathematical education.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>3D models for clinical training</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/07/30/3D_clinical/"/>
		<updated>2013-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/07/30/3D_clinical</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-9bSce_VZSOU/UffkEw4Ck-I/AAAAAAAAz-Y/JflPNKPfy6g/w506-h285/Desktop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D models have typically been used for training with a number of clinical specialties, and we are now experimenting with orthopedic fractures and dentistry prostheses. The possibilities are endless, but one that is of particular interest to me is the ability to enhance training and assessment in relation to diagnosis, disease mechanisms or pathophysiology, and therapeutic planning. Here are some examples in the context of orthopedic fractures, a topic that is of interest not only to orthopedic surgeons and residents but also to the large number of other health care providers involved with the treatment of bone fractures such as nurses, physical and occupational therapists, general practitioners, among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diagnosis: even very large clinical image repositories can be difficult to search when looking for specific types of fractures and their multiple combinations. With 3D models you cannot only reproduce any type of fracture, but also any combination. This is important for novice healthcare providers since they rarely have an opportunity to see a large collection all in one place. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pathophysiology or fracture biomechanics: the biomechanics of a fracture largely determines its treatment. In other words, how the fragments are displaced as a function of their muscle and ligament insertions, gravity, or walking load will largely determine whether a fracture might be successfuly treated with a conservative treatment or the multiple types of surgical devices. In a 3D model it is possible to demonstrate the impact of the biomechanical factors on the fracture, such as having fragments being pulled in one direction or another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treatment: 3D can demonstrate with extreme clarity how a cast or an orthopedic device interact with a the biomechanics of a fracture, counterbalancing these mechanisms to bring the fragments to their anatomical position. This is certainly useful when attempting to explain the preference for one treatment vs. another.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring this back to an educational context, the main role of these 3D models is to have healthcare providers build rich maps with the concepts and situations surrounding therapeutic planning. In other words, rather than having oversimplistic associations saying that for a given fracture type the treatment should be x, you build a number of rich associations having biomechanical mechanisms in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>