<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	
	<title type="text" xml:lang="en"></title>
	<link type="application/atom+xml" href="http://rpietro.github.io/feed/" rel="self"/>
 	<link type="text" href="hhttp://rpietro.github.io/" rel="alternate"/>
	<updated>2013-10-09T10:03:05-04:00</updated>
	<id>http://http://rpietro.github.io/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Ricardo Pietrobon</name>
	</author>
	<rights>Copyright (c) 2013, Ricardo Pietrobon; all rights reserved.</rights>
	
	
	<entry>
		<title>Are you primarily aiming at educating readers in the Introduction section of your original paper? If so, stop!</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/literature/2013/10/10/review-intro/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/literature/2013/10/10/review-intro</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Are you primarily aiming at educating readers in the Introduction section of your original paper? If so, stop!&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a common misconception that the primary goal of the literature review in the Introduction section of an original scientific article is to educate readers. Why readers will be somewhat educated about the main areas of your paper while reading the Introduction, having education as a primary purpose of the Introduction will almost necessarily mislead your readers. Here are the primary reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why should you focus on a gap rather than education?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are writing an original paper, the first task in a paper is to convince readers that the problem you will be addressing is indeed novel. The primary goal of the Introduction is to establish, beyond any reasonable doubt, that the topic is indeed novel. Put in another way, the primary goal of the literature review in the Introduction is to establish that the information gap addressed by the paper is a true gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;But is there a problem in focusing on education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary problem in focusing on education as the primary goal is that the literature will be unfocused. As a fictitious example, imagine that an author wants to write an original clinical research paper on the effect diabetes on mortality after appendectomy in elderly patients. If the author introduces a section in the Introduction talking about the molecular pathophysiology of diabetes, there will be at least two main problems from the readers&amp;#39; perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, readers will be distracted, since pathophysiology is not relevant to establish that no previous study has ever been conducted regarding the relationship between diabetes and clinical outcomes. Second, if the author does talk about the molecular pathophysiology of diabetes, readers will automatically assume that the article will focus on some basic science aspect of the problem. Since they will later on find that this is not the case, they will be frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How can you review the literature on gap since the information does not exist?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an author then decides that focusing on the gap is the way to go, how can you then conduct a literature review on a gap? In other words, how can you review the literature on something that you yourself claims is novels and therefore has not been done before?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer here is to review literature on the fringes of your gap, and then keep pointing to your gap to emphasize that the gap is indeed a gap. For example, if the proposed gap is the absence of literature on the relationship between diabetes and surgical outcomes after appendectomy in the elderly, then one strategy would be to review similar studies that are not in the elderly, emphasizing since the elderly have a different response to diabetes the results could be different. Other approaches could be to evaluate a narrow section of the literature of the impact of diabetes on post-operative outcomes or a review of other studies evaluating post appendectomy studies involving the elderly. After each of these, the author then emphasizes that, despiting knowing what is known in the field, the original gap has not been filled and, therefore, it is the objective of the current study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Us Brazil</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//2013/10/09/us-brazil/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//2013/10/09/us-brazil</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;layout: post
title:  &amp;quot;Orientando pesquisadores: Qual a diferença entre a vida acadêmica em uma universidade americana e brasileira?&amp;quot;
date:   2013-10-09&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;categories: situated&lt;em&gt;cognition, big&lt;/em&gt;data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-vU_10wGtzj0/Uk3FaoxcuqI/AAAAAAAA4iw/AtFaPbqDK0I/w748-h561-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Us Brazil&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professores, pesquisadores e estudantes brasileiros frequentemente me perguntam sobre as diferenças entre a vida acadêmica em uma universidade americana e brasileira. Apesar de nunca haver trabalhado profissionalmente em uma universidade brasileira, eu tenho colaborado com professores e estudantes brasileiros desde o início da minha carreira. Nos Estados Unidos minha principal experiência é com a Duke University, mas tambem trabalhei em colaboração com professores em várias outras instituições. O texto abaixo tenta resumir o meu ponto de vista pessoal sobre as principais diferenças:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Uma moeda única&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No Brasil as métricas para avaliação de produtividade acadêmica são variadas, envolvendo conceitos com colaborações internacionais, número de alunos orientados para mestrado ou doutorado, atividades educacionais, interface com indústria, atividades acadêmicas administrativas, entre outros. Nisso o Brasil segue uma linha que é comum em vários paises na Ásia e Europa. Nos EUA, apesar de universidades diferentes apresentarem métricas institucionais diferentes, na prática a métrica se reduz a uma única coisa: Trazer recursos financeiros para a sua pesquisa dentro da instituição. Uma segunda métrica relacionada a primeira é a geração de publicações originais em revistas de alto impacto. Apesar de uma série de tentativas de valorização de outras métricas, e um todo um discurso retórico institucional, na prática todo o restante é secundário. Por exemplo, no setor de pesquisa biomédica atividades clínicas são consideradas uma importante fonte de renda e professores são fortemente encorajados a manter os seus volumes de pacientes tão ocupados quanto possível, mas em termos de reconhecimento acadêmico o trabalho clínico é quase irrelevante. Orientar estudantes de pós-graduação é consideado bom, desde que essa orientação seja financiada por alguma agência de financiamento externa, ao contrário essa atividade será vista como um item de despesa no orçamento. Mesmo os artigos originais que possam representar contribuições para o campo podem ser considerados secundários se não forem apoiados por financiamento externo. E por último, um financiamento que venha de uma instituição de prestígio como o &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nih.gov/&quot;&gt;National Institutes of Health (NIH)&lt;/a&gt; é preferível a um financiamento via indústria. No entanto, se o valor vindo da indústria for alto, ninguém irá reclamar, apesar de que isso está mais e mais difícil com a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.news-republic.com/Web/ArticleWeb.aspx?regionid=1&amp;amp;articleid=13666655&quot;&gt;crise da indústria farmacêutica mundial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Professores são responsáveis por cobrir o seu próprio salário&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embora haja variações entre diferentes universidades, há duas categorias principais de professores: Professores de pesquisa (Research Professors) e Professores em um &lt;em&gt;tenure track&lt;/em&gt;. Professores de pesquisa são responsáveis por cobrir os seus salários por meio de financiamento de pesquisa. Caso eles não consigam cobrir pelo menos uma boa parte do seu salário eles sao demitidos. Ao contrário dos professores de pesquisa, outros professores que tenham um maior potencial começam suas carreira com um tenure-track. No tenure-track depois de algo em torno de oito a dez anos, eles são avaliados e nesse momento ou são promovidos para uma posição de tenure ou são &amp;quot;convidados a sair&amp;quot;. Os que receberem a tenure não podem mais ser mandados a não ser em casos extremos, como por exemplo quando seja comprovada fraude científica ou no caso de haver um relacionamento amoroso com um estudante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Mérito e política&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em contraste com muitos países na America Latina, Europa e Ásia, promoções e até mesmo ser contratado como professor é uma questão primariamente de mérito e bem menos de política. Obviamente, egos, alianças políticas e contar vantagem podem ajudar, mas esses fatores geralmente não se sustentam a longo prazo a não ser que o professor consiga atingir a métrica central: trazer financiamento para a universidade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Atividades de empreendedorismo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A criação de empresas por professores, as assim chamadas &amp;quot;start-ups&amp;quot;, é uma tendência crescente nos EUA. E por boas razões: com o crescimento do sistema de pesquisa nos EUA, a capacidade do governo para financiá-lo é limitada, havendo uma necessidade urgente de integrar a produtividade acadêmica com necessidades reais da sociedade. Apesar de toda uma retórica de apoio ao empreendedorismo, a universidade é uma organização muito grande e geralmente lenta, onde os hábitos antigos persistem por um tempo prolongado. Isso significa que apesar de todo um discurso pró-empreendedorismo a moeda única ainda prevalece: Aquisição de financiamento é considerado imensamente mais importante do que a criação de empresas. Como as atividades empresariais não são um método particularmente eficaz para atrair financiamento na maioria dos casos, nesse momento há muito mais conversa do que ação em relação a realmente promover a criação de startups, apesar de que existem instituições que fogem a essa regra e provem ambientes realmente fecundos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. Cérebros, egos e orientadores&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nas melhores universidades americanas a fama dos professores normalmente se conecta a realidade, e que quer dizer que você se vê circundado por pessoas realmente inteligentes, gerando idéias excelentes. Obviamente, esses grandes cérebros são, muito frequentemente mas não necessariamente, acompanhados de egos que superam em muito o tamanho dos cérebros. Ou seja, se você tem as habilidades políticas para lidar com esses egos a possibilidade de sucesso é grande. Mas sempre, apesar de manobras políticas ajudarem, a moeda única de atração de financiamento predomina, e sem ela a política sozinha não vai levar a lugar algum. Em relação a orientadores, existem bons e maus orientadores. Algumas pessoas simplesmente tem sorte e conseguem encontrar um verdadeiro orientador que vá guiá-lo. Eu tive essa sorte. Tendo dito isso, os orientandos absolutamente não devem esperar que os seus orientadores irão lhes dizer tudo o que deve ser feito. A iniciativa é essencial, assim como a capacidade de trabalho sem esperar que o seu orientador vá monitorá-lo. A expectativa e que todos os que estejam trabalhando sejam profissionais maduros e com responsabilidade. Outros tem menos sorte vão cair com alguém que não se vê como um verdadeiro orientador.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;escrito por Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: How to cite a reference in an original article: Despite what you think, it might not be so obvious</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/literature/2013/10/08/how-cite/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/literature/2013/10/08/how-cite</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-qyZ16xzg3Ak/Ukg5Pu5vxtI/AAAAAAAA4eU/l4TbFIWZk7g/w672-h504-no/fract65.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: How to cite a reference in an original article: Despite what you think, it might not be so obvious&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most novice researchers make mistakes when citing a reference, and often times those mistakes go unnoticed for years, if caught at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always cite the primary reference. In other words, if you are citing a paper because it mentions something that was as result of yet another paper, you are doing the wrong thing. Papers should be cited by something they have done. For example, a result they had, a methodology they used, or an opinion regarding their results stated in the Discussion section. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the article you are citing in full text. Do not cite an article merely because you read its abstract. Worse yet, do not cite an article because other articles have also cited it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unless an article is a landmark study in the topic you are discussing, do not describe it in isolation. In other words, cite article in perspective of other similar articles might have done. For example, instead of saying that Smith et al. have had such and such methods reaching such and such results, aggregate all articles talking about a certain topic and describe that topic as a whole in light of clusters of articles agreeing or disagreeing with a certain position.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In an ideal scenario, keep your references organized so that you know exactly which sections of a given article support whatever you might have used it for. For example, if you cite Smith at al. because that article reports a mortality rate of 2%, then your reference manager software should store the reference to Smith at al. along with the paragraphs in that paper where the 2% mortality rate are stated. Although this might sound like an overkill, this is a new trend and already present in reference management software such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://jabref.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;JabRef&lt;/a&gt; combined with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://trinker.github.io/reports/&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; package.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Why avoiding spreadsheets such as Microsoft Excel as the way to store your research data is likely not a good idea</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/data,/facebook/2013/10/07/excel-collection/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/data,/facebook/2013/10/07/excel-collection</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vpQCVUeSEvc/Ukg4rlMSkdI/AAAAAAAA4dk/3Yl_PW3_g8E/w506-h380/fractals45.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: Why avoiding spreadsheets such as Microsoft Excel as the way to store your research data is likely not a good idea&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, spreadsheets are as useful as a software can get. That being said, using spreadsheets as the primary means of collecting your data is inherently a bad idea. Here are some of the reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No protection: once the data is entered, it is very easy to either delete it or replace a correct value with an incorrect one. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No versioning: If you keep adding data to the same spreadsheet, you really cannot go back in time to know who made which modifications at which time. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/%E2%80%8E&quot;&gt;Google sheets&lt;/a&gt; is better in this regarding since it does have a versioning system that is mostly reliable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard to share: sure you can place a spreadsheet in a system such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;, where multiple people can access it, but if any two people attempt to change the same spreadsheet at the same time there will be a conflict. Google sheets is slightly better in this regard since you can share the sheet with other collaborators who will then be able to see if somebody if somebody else is editing the sheet at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy: if you collect sensitive data, such as biomedical data, spreadsheets are not safe at all and could expose information that could compromise the privacy of patients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution then is to use one of the many &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_data_capture&quot;&gt;electronic data capture systems&lt;/a&gt;, out there which will take care of each of these problems. &lt;a href=&quot;http://project-redcap.org/&quot;&gt;RedCap&lt;/a&gt; is one that comes to mind as being not only very good but also increasingly used by a number of researchers conducting prospective data collection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: What is truly valued in an academic life in the US?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/networking/2013/10/06/academic-life-us/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/networking/2013/10/06/academic-life-us</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-ul3-okePKVo/Ukg3u2Tr4-I/AAAAAAAA4c4/VTmETF6gh-w/w506-h380/frac.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: What is truly valued in an academic life in the US?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A frequent question when I travel abroad to give courses on research methodology is &lt;em&gt;how does the academic life in the US differ from here&lt;/em&gt;. Now, of course &lt;em&gt;here&lt;/em&gt; will differ whether I might be in Europe, Asia, or South America. With that disclosure, here is an attempt to summarize the main differences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two currencies: In different countries promotion will depend on metrics such as international collaborations, number of MSc or PhD students, educational activities, entrepreneurial activities, administrative academic activities, among others. In contrast, in the US two currencies are almost unparalleled: Funding the professor might bring in, and high impact original publications. Despite a number of attempts to value different efforts and accomplishments, and many speeches by administrative officers, everything else is significantly secondary. For example, in the biomedical sector clinical activities are considered an important source of revenue and faculty members are strongly encouraged to keep their schedules very busy, but in terms of academic recognition the clinical work is almost irrelevant. Mentoring students or other faculty members is considered nice, but unless it comes along with funding to support those efforts it is viewed as a budget expense. Even original articles that might represent contributions to the field are looked down if they are not supported by funding. And then, when it comes to funding, something coming from the National Institutes of Health is preferred in comparison with industry funding, although if the amount from industry is substantial nobody will complain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professors are responsible to cover for their own salary: Although there are variations across different universities, there are two main classes (some people would call casts) of professors: Research and tenure track professors. Research professors are responsible to cover their salaries through funded research, and if they cannot cover their own salaries they will be dismissed. Tenure track positions are offered at the very beginning to those who are perceived as having a greater potential. After a certain period of time, usually around eight to ten years, the tenure-track professors will be evaluated and either promoted to tenure or, again, asked to leave. If they receive tenure, then they can only be dismissed in extreme cases, such as scientific fraud or having an affair with a student. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merit and politics: In contrast with many countries, promotions and even being hired as a professor is a matter of merit and far less of politics. Sure, egos, political alliances, and hot air still go around and can help, but they usually won&amp;#39;t be sustained unless the professor can deliver the two main metrics: funding and high impact publications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurial activities: Forming startup companies is the new hype in the US, and for good reasons: The research system has outgrown the government capacity to fund it, and there is a dire need to integrate the ivory towers with the rest of society. Despite a lot of speeches, the university is usually a very large and slow-moving organization, and old habits die hard. All this means is that the two currencies still prevail: Funding and publications. Since entrepreneurial activities are not a particularly strong method to attract neither in most cases, at this point there is much more talk than action, a few institutions around the country probably being the exception.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brains, egos, and mentors: At the top American universities the hype will usually meet the reality, and you are usually truly surrounded by smart people with excellent ideas. Of course, those big brains are very often, but not necessarily accompanied by huge egos. If you have the political skills or massaging abilities to deal with the egos you will do well, again provided that you can deliver the required currencies. As for mentors, it is usually a hit or miss. Some people like me are simply lucky and will encounter true mentors who will teach you the path and guide you through it. Others are less lucky and will struggle by falling under somebody who doesn&amp;#39;t see himself as a true mentor and a coach. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Coaching researchers: Data dictionaries are a central piece in any article focusing on analyzing an existing database</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/data,/facebook/2013/10/05/data-dictionaries/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/data,/facebook/2013/10/05/data-dictionaries</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-uNWdfkWgrd0/Ukg3RCycHDI/AAAAAAAA4cc/lhepxoVzW7c/w672-h504-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: Coaching researchers: Data dictionaries are a central piece in any article focusing on analyzing an existing database&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a researcher plans a paper based on an existing database, one of the central considerations is that no results in the paper will be possible unless they are backed up by existing questions that have been asked within that database. In a future post I will contradict myself by saying that databases can be enriched and extended, but for now let us assume that their content is fixed in relation to what they can contain. This makes the data dictionary, or the collection of questions, the platform that will serve as the basis for every subsequent step in process of creating the manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you now believe that creating a data dictionary should be your first step after deciding that you will publish a manuscript, what are exactly the components of a data dictionary you should be putting together? Here you go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variables: When you think about a regular prospective study, you can think of a variable as the questions asked in a form. If you think of a database as a spreadsheet, then the variables will be the names of the columns in that sheet. Still using the sheet example, each observation will be a separate row containing information about a patient or whatever even might be measured. Depending on what kind of data scientist you talk to, they might use the term field or class to represent a variable, but in the end it is all the same. A final detail is that a properly named variable will mean something to you when you first read it. For example, a good variable name is age&lt;em&gt;years which you will almost immediately identify as a variable measuring age in years. In contrast a variable called xx&lt;/em&gt;23 will let you wondering what it might mean, which is not good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Variable definition: A variable definition is simply what was asked in order to get the data. For example, a variable called age_years could have been generated from a question such as &amp;quot;What is your current age?&amp;quot; Having a definition is important because if that variable had been generated from something like a date of birth the interpretation would be slightly different. If you might be wondering why, well, several studies have shown that, surprise surprise, people tend to lie about their age when asked directly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternative options: Alternative options are whatever options a person might have been given when answering the question. For example, if the variable age had a field where a number could be inserted would be a very different scenario from that field having broad age categories such as 0-10, 10-20, ... as the latter contains less information than the former.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type of alternative options: The type of variable could be something like continuous (numbers which include decimals), integers, time, nominal categories (white, black, ...), ordinal (education level as elementary, high school, college), dichotomous (yes/no), among others. The type of alternative options will be important later on as they are one of the factors in deciding what type of data analysis methods might be used to extract information from them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Missing and implausible values: Missing values is simply information that has not been filled out. As every basic stats book will tell you, missing is very different from a value of zero, as missing means that you don&amp;#39;t know what value to assign to that cell, while missing is ... missing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Why should qualitative research matter?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook,/analysis/2013/10/04/qualitative-res/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook,/analysis/2013/10/04/qualitative-res</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xT0kLYdxqP4/Ukg2A4tvH6I/AAAAAAAA4bk/kWI1mM0XZKA/w672-h504-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: Why should qualitative research matter?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When most researchers talk about clinical research, most people will make an instant connection with studies where everything is quantified. Whether it is an experimental study such as a randomized trial or an observational study, everything has to be represented by a number or a category. What most of these people miss, however, is that results from quantitative research can hardly be evaluated in the absence of context, and context is qualitative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a simple example: There is a humongous amount of research regarding healthcare disparities, the vast majority of them demonstrating that racial minorities usually have worse results when treated for a given condition. What is often uncertain however, is why that might be the case. For example, is is because there is racial discrimination? Communication problems? Issues in accessing care? All of the above? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where qualitative research comes in, because to even create a hypothesis about why a certain factor might be a player in the disparity scenario, a researcher first has to know that that factor exists. For example, if I attempt to study a group where disparities abound, but I don&amp;#39;t even think about the possibility of that phenomenon being related to mistrust issues among the minority group, the researcher might misinterpret the disparity as being caused by the healthcare provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in order to properly measure all the different aspects during the quantitative study, it is important to have a deep qualitative understanding of the phenomenon. Back to our example regarding mistrust, unless a researcher has a deep understanding about the various components of mistrust, it would be impossible to capture the underlying causes. For example, are the main underlying factors issues such as historical events, the fact that healthcare providers are perceived as being from a racial or ethnic group that is different from theirs, or whatever else might be underlying the issue. The fact is that without qualitative research it is virtually impossible to determine what will have to measured in the quantitative portion of the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, one of the big misconceptions about qualitative research is that it has to entirely precede the quantitative components. The problem with that concept is that if in order to conduct a quantitative study we have to wait for the qualitative to be completed, the full study would take a really long time. Instead, an ideal workflow would be to have iterative cycles of short studies where the qualitative results help guide the quantitative ones, and the quantitative studies would help point the qualitative ones to the areas where more depth is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Pair programming as a strategy to learn how to program?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/10/03/pair-programming/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/10/03/pair-programming</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-xT0kLYdxqP4/Ukg2A4tvH6I/AAAAAAAA4bk/kWI1mM0XZKA/w672-h504-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Pair programming as a strategy to learn how to program?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time somebody asks a question on a title you bet the answer will be yes. But here the answer is maybe, but I really don&amp;#39;t know. I recently read an excellent post on pair programming, which is one of the pillars behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://xprogramming.com/what-is-extreme-programming/&quot;&gt;XP (eXtreme Programming)&lt;/a&gt;. It is interesting that a few years ago there was almost a taboo talking about remote pair programming, for example with two programmers working together through a screen sharing app. But now it seems like the remote pair programming has gone mainstream, which I find pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one topic that I have not seen addressed and that I haven&amp;#39;t tried myself is whether pair programming could be used so that one of the parties could learn how to program. When I say learn I don&amp;#39;t mean to take one person who knows absolutely nothing about programming as that will likely slow down the main programmer. But if the learner knows how to program in another language then she can provide some insights without necessarily know the syntax. Although as I said I haven&amp;#39;t tried it, the key for this to work is for the learner to have the sensibility not to get in the way of the main programmer, otherwise productivity will go down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps something to be tested ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Why should biomedical researchers learn R?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/analysis/2013/10/02/why-r/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/analysis/2013/10/02/why-r</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-tYIssxIGpvs/Ukg0cnmzGbI/AAAAAAAA4a4/LNPARlsBW3c/w741-h504-no/fract.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: Why should biomedical researchers learn R?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; is the language of choice for a large number of data scientists. And for good reasons, including the outstanding group of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.r-project.org/contributors.html&quot;&gt;core developers&lt;/a&gt;, a huge number of &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/available_packages_by_name.html&quot;&gt;packages&lt;/a&gt; covering almost everything imaginable, and a language combining object orientation and functions that is easy to learn if you have some previous programming experience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to biomedical researchers, however, the prerequisite of having some previous programming experience is missing in most of the cases, and that creates a problem. The end result is that every time I mention R as a possible language, the reaction is almost invariably that (a) R is hard to learn and (b) &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; is what I am using now since it is &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; will usually translate into SPSS, Stata, or SAS-JMP, and &lt;em&gt;easy&lt;/em&gt; usually means that there is a graphical user interface for them to point &amp;amp; click and do their own analyses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast with most people in what I call the old statistics school, I am absolutely in favor of biomedical researchers directly working with their data. The concerns from the old school stem, in their words, from a concern of biomedical researchers getting results results that they don&amp;#39;t understand and, worse, propagating those results as if they were valid. I share that concern and think that it is legitimate. In most cases, however, the true, vested concern from the old school is actually simpler: Turf protection. I disagree entirely, and think that biomedical researchers not playing with their data are simply shifting the errors in interpretation to the statistician or data scientist since the latter do not have the biomedical insights to explore the data sets as they should be explored. Where I am trying to get with this is that if the biomedical researcher works alone or the statistician/data scientist is not supported by the full insights from the biomedical researcher, the odds of having incomplete or misleading information is significantly increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what does all this have to do with R? Well, if we agree that the way to go is to have teams where biomedical researchers have insights from their field and data scientists know their methods in depth, then biomedical researchers need to understand what data scientists are saying and doing. This is where R comes in. So, in an ideal research team, biomedical researchers would know at least the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read an R source code: in other words, which tests and models are being run and with which variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpret whether the choice of tests and models were appropriate given the type of variables serving as input to them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpret the general results of each test and model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, it&amp;#39;s not even to write code, but instead to &lt;em&gt;critically&lt;/em&gt; read code. I also think that the ability to explore the data set is incredibly useful, and this can certainly be done with a graphical user interface, in R or any other software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Orientando pesquisadores: Sete motivos pelos quais pesquisadores brasileiros podem ter dificuldade ao tentar publicar em revistas internacionais de alto impacto</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook,/errors/2013/10/01/seven-errors-pt/"/>
		<updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook,/errors/2013/10/01/seven-errors-pt</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Orientando pesquisadores: Sete motivos pelos quais pesquisadores brasileiros podem ter dificuldade ao tentar publicar em revistas internacionais de alto impacto&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-joKOP9Mu7Sw/UkLT_Zfc_II/AAAAAAAA4Ug/aAxdWZ-8kg8/w706-h353-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muitas vezes pesquisadores brasileiros que são bem sucedidos com publicações em revistas brasileiras acabam tendo dificuldade quando tentam publicar em revistas de maior impacto a nível internacional. Abaixo estão algumas das razões mais frequentes pelas quais isso pode ocorrer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Não focar em uma verdadeira lacuna na literatura&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por definição, um artigo original tem de se concentrar em algo que seja realmente novo. Apesar da necessidade de focar em algo novo, muitos pesquisadores só realizam uma revisão superficial de literatura no início do projeto. Como consequência, muitas vezes eles acabam descobrindo ao final do projeto que a idéia já havia sido explorada em várias outras publicações, reduzindo a possibilidade de publicação em uma revista de alto impacto internacional. Alguma soluções possíveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realizar uma revisão de literatura minuciosa no início do seu projeto. Se a pergunta já foi respondida por outra pessoa, então esse é o momento perfeito para mudar a sua abordagem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Se alguém já fez o que você estava pensando em fazer, use aquele artigo como base e partir dele foque em algo que ainda não foi explorado, utilize uma metodologia mais sofisticada, ou mude a sua pergunta de pesquisa completamente.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Não focar em problemas que possam ser generalizados para além do Brasil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embora focar a sua pesquisa em um problema que esteja presente apenas no Brasil seja perfeitamente válida, ao tentar publicar este artigo internacionalmente o editor da revista pode afirmar que como o foco é restrito ao Brasil você deveria publicá-lo em uma revista brasileira. Alguma soluções possíveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Se você focar o seu projeto em um problema que é exclusivamente local, tente tirar conclusões que possam ser generalizadas para outros países com condições semelhantes. Por exemplo, uma doença que é comum no Brasil também pode ser comum na Rússia ou China. O sistema de saúde brasileiro pode ser semelhante a outros países da América Latina.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evite argumentar que a lacuna no conhecimento que o seu artigo aborde seja a ausência de informação somente no contexto brasileiro. Enquanto você certamente deve mencionar que o seu estudo foi realizado no Brasil, se você enfatizar que a principal lacuna abordada pelo seu estudo é que o assunto nunca foi estudado no Brasil, isso provavelmente vai diminuir o interesse do editor já que os leitores ao redor do mundo não vão estar interessados no que você tem a dizer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Não seguir as normas internacionais sobre como reportar um artigo utilizando uma determinada metodologia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ao longo da última década, uma série de normas internacionais sobre como reportar artigos científico foram publicadas, e algumas dessas normas são inclusive mandatórias para certas revistas. Isto significa que se você desenhar ou reportar o seu estudo sem levar essas normas em consideração, o seu artigo pode não ser nem enviado aos revisores, o editor rejeitando o artigo já em uma primeira instância. Alguma soluções possíveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Esteja ciente sobre as normas existentes. Um ótimo site sobre essas normas é a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.equator-network.org/&quot;&gt;Equator Network&lt;/a&gt;, que é provavelmente a maior coleção de normas desse tipo na Web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estude o padrão em detalhes quando você estiver desenhando o seu estudo, e não apenas depois de completar a coleta de dados e análise. Embora as normas destinem-se para fins de como reportar um artigo, se você não seguir estas normas desde o início do seu projeto, você provavelmente não terá coletado as informações necessárias para poder seguir essas mesmas normas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Não escrever usando um &amp;quot;português americanizado&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Com as ferramentas de tradução automática ficando melhor a cada dia, e tradutores profissionais de qualidade disponíveis via a internet, os pesquisadores muitas vezes pensam que escrever um artigo científico com o mesmo estilo ou estrutura de qualquer outro documento em português seja satisfatório. A má notícia é que não é bem assim. Se você usar uma estrutura normal da língua portuguesa e depois tentar a tradução via um tradutor automático como o &lt;a href=&quot;http://translate.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Translate&lt;/a&gt; ou mesmo tendo tradutor profissional revisando o seu trabalho, os resultados tendem a ser de ruins a desastrosos. Alguma soluções possíveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Escreva em seu próprio idioma, mas usando um &amp;quot;português americanizado&amp;quot;. Isto significa que você deve ter não só frases curtas, mas escrever em voz ativa e acima de tudo evitar palavras desnecessárias.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Muito cuidado com as palavras técnicas, já que normalmente nem tradutores automáticos nem profissionais sabem como traduzi-los seguindo o que normalmente é feito dentro de um determinado campo científico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. Não trabalhar em uma verdadeira colaboração com os chamados cientistas de dados&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antigamente, pesquisadores não quantitativos muitas vezes desenhavam seus estudos, coletavam seus dados e ao final enviavam tudo para um estatístico. Nesse momento, os estatísticos se queixavam de que eles não estavam envolvidos desde a fase de desenho, mas eles também não faziam qualquer esforço para ensinar os pesquisadores sobre os conceitos básicos de estatística, ja que isso poderia fazer com que eles perdessem a sua função. Este tipo de &amp;quot;colaboração&amp;quot; claramente não funciona. Alguma soluções possíveis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Se você não é um pesquisador quantitativo, você necessariamente tem de aprender o mínimo necessário para ser capaz de estabelecer uma conversa com o cientista de dados ou estatístico no seu grupo. Esse conhecimento mínimo significa, pelo menos, saber em que situações certos modelos de testes estatísticos devem ser utilizados e, em seguida, como interpretar os resultados provenientes deles. Resumindo: Se você atualmente tem confiança de que o seu estatístico entende todos os aspectos não quantitativos do seu estudo necessários para fazer uma análise adequada, você está se enganando.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Se você não é um assim chamado cientista de dados ou estatístico e você está fazendo a sua análise sozinho, pare imediatamente. Só porque você pode clicar nos botões do SPSS não significa que você deve estar trabalhando sozinho. Há uma série de pressupostos e complexidades inerentes a interpretação da maioria das análises que podem levá-lo a erros grosseiros de interpretação. Resumindo: você deve trabalhar em equipes. É mais divertido e definitivamente levará a um melhor aproveitamento do tempo de todos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Não alinhar a lacuna, objetivo e principais resultados do seu artigo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muitos livros e cursos sobre escrita científica irão dizer que o seu artigo deve ser focado num único tópico ou que ele deveria dizer uma coisa única. Eles estão certos quando dizem isso, mas a imensa maioria nunca realmente especificam exatamente o que isso significa. Aqui está uma breve descrição do que isso quer dizer na prática:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seu artigo deve ser focado em uma lacuna existente na literatura, algo sobre o qual outros pesquisadores não tenham focado antes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No decorrer do artigo a sua lacuna irá se transformar no objetivo de estudo. Gap e objetivo são, literalmente, um o espelho do outro. Isso significa que você não deve direcionar a atenção do leitor para uma lacuna a menos que você não pretenda fazer dessa lacuna um objetivo do seu estudo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Os seus três ou quatro resultados principais devem estar alinhados ao objetivo que você definiu anteriormente. Quando todos os três componentes estão alinhados, o seu editor e leitores irão sentir que o seu trabalho tem um foco único já que todos estão falando sobre a mesma coisa. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;7. Não desenvolver uma estória narrativa ao discutir a literatura&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ao rever a literatura em um artigo original, muitas vezes é tentador começar a ler um determinado artigo, adicionar um pedaço de informação dele no seu artigo, depois de ler outro artigo e imediatamente inserir mais um pedacinho, e assim por diante. O resultado final, frequentemente, é um texto aos pedaços que soa desconectado. Soluções:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Não escreva a sua revisão de literatura na introdução ou discussão até que você tenha um conhecimento profundo da literatura.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depois de uma revisão da literatura, desenvolva um esboço do que você gostaria de dizer. Tenha em mente que a revisão da literatura para a Introdução e a Discussão têm papéis completamente diferentes e por isso devem ser escritas de modo diverso.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A partir do seu esboço, desenvolva uma narrativa que conte uma história que possa manter os seus leitores interessados.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todos esses temas e muito mais serão abordados em posts futuros. Então, fique atento e se junte ao nosso &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/170343223157225/&quot;&gt;grupo no Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, de modo que você possa saber cada vez que algo novo surgiu. Espero que gostem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;escrito por Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Seven reasons why researchers around the world might have difficulty when attempting to publish in high impact, international journals</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/30/seven-reasons/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/30/seven-reasons</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-joKOP9Mu7Sw/UkLT_Zfc_II/AAAAAAAA4Ug/aAxdWZ-8kg8/w706-h353-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Coaching researchers: Seven reasons why researchers around the world might have difficulty when attempting to publish in high impact, international journals&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers who have been successful in publishing in journals within their own countries will often find it hard to have their articles accepted when moving to higher impact, international journals. Below are some of the most frequent reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Not focusing on a real gap in the literature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By definition, an original article has to focus on something that is truly novel. Despite the crucial importance of novelty, many researchers will only perform a casual literature review at the beginning of the project, just to find out at the end that their project was everything but novel. Solutions then are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct a thorough literature review at the very beginning of your project. If the question has already been answered by somebody else, then that is the right time to change your approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If somebody has already done what you were planning on doing, build upon that publication to narrow the focus down to something that has not been explored, use a significantly better methodology, or change your research question altogether.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Not focusing on issues that might generalize beyond your country&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although focusing on a problem that is present only within your country is certainly valuable, when attempting to publish this internationally your editors might tell you to publish in your own country. Solutions then are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you focus on something that is very local, try to draw conclusions that might generalize to other, similar countries. For example, a disease that is common in Brazil might also be common in Russian or China.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid making the gap of your study country-specific. While you certainly have to mention where your study was conducted, if you emphasize that the main gap of your study is that the topic has never been studied in your country, then that might decrease the interest from editors since readers outside of your country will not be interested in what you have to say.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not following international reporting standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, a number of international reporting standards have been released, and some of them are even made mandatory for certain journals. This means that if you either design or report your study without taking these standards into consideration, your article might not even pass the initial editor review. Solutions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be aware of the existing standards. A central resource is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.equator-network.org/&quot;&gt;Equator Network&lt;/a&gt;, which contains what is probably the largest collection of standards on the Web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Study the standard in detail when you are designing the study, not only after you complete it. Although the standard is meant for reporting purposes, if you don&amp;#39;t get the design right from the beginning then you will not be able to follow the reporting guideline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not writing in a &amp;quot;scientific English&amp;quot; structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With automatic translation tools getting better and better, and human translators being available everywhere, people will often think that writing a scientific paper like they would write any other document should be OK. Well, it&amp;#39;s not. Whether you use an automatic translator like &lt;a href=&quot;http://translate.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Translate&lt;/a&gt; or a human translator, if you write the sentences in the typical structure of your own language, results will tend to be disastrous. Solutions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write in your own language but using an &amp;quot;Americanized language structure.&amp;quot; This means things such as short sentences, active voice, and avoiding unnecessary words at all costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watch out for technical words, as neither automatic nor human translators will usually know how to translate them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not working in a true collaboration with data scientists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days, non-quantitative researchers such as those working in the biomedical field would often design their studies, collect their data, and then send everything to a statistician. Then, although statisticians would complain that they were not involved in the design phase, they would also not make any effort to teach researchers the basics of statistics since that would be considered an invasion of their turf. This type of practice clearly won&amp;#39;t work anymore. Solutions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not a quantitative researcher, you have to learn the bare minimum to be able to talk with the data scientist or statistician in your group. The bare minimum means at least knowing in which situation certain tests of models are to be used, and then how to interpret the results coming out of them. So, if you are trusting that your data scientist will know everything, you are utterly wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are not a data scientist or statistician and you are doing your analysis alone, stop. Just because you can click the buttons in SPSS doesn&amp;#39;t mean you should be working alone. There are a number of assumptions and intricacies in interpreting most analyses that might make you trip and fall. In sum, work in a team. It&amp;#39;s more fun and definitely a better use of everybody&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not aligning the gap, objective, and main results of your paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many books and courses on scientific writing will tell you that your article should be focused, or that it should say one single thing. They are right, but they never really tell you exactly what that means. So, here is a short description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your article should initially focus on a gap in the literature, something that other researchers have not focused on before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your gap will then translate into your study objective. Gap and objective are literally mirrors of each other, meaning that you should not point to a gap unless you intend to answer it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your main three or four results should answer the objective you have set for yourself. When all three components are aligned, then your editor and your readers and your editor will feel that your paper has focus and is worth publishing and reading. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Not developing a narrative when discussing the literature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reviewing the literature in an original paper, it&amp;#39;s often tempting to start reading a given paper and then adding a piece of information about it, then reading another and then add another chunk, and then keep doing this over and over. The end result will often look choppy and disconnected. Solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not write your literature review in the Introduction or Discussion without having a thorough understanding of the literature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once you have reviewed the literature, develop an outline of what you would like to say. Bear in mind that the literature review for the Introduction and the Discussion have completely different roles and so should be written with a different goal in mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From that outline, then develop a narrative that will simply tell a story that is good enough to keep your readers engaged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these topics and much more will be covered in future posts. So, stay tuned and join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/170343223157225/&quot;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; so that you can know every time something new has come up. Hope you enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Why on earth would you use Jekyll for education blogging?</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/29/jekyll-education/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/29/jekyll-education</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-JNtZ2WTQaZc/UkSAWXGLbbI/AAAAAAAA4Wg/vo4auLZ4TOc/w825-h561-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt;Why on earth would you use Jekyll for education blogging?&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently posted about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/19/markdown/&quot;&gt;use of Markdown for learning materials&lt;/a&gt;, and what I perceive as its advantages. A topic related to Markdown are static blogs such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, since Jekyll allows users to write in Markdown. My goal here is to report on my experience with Jekyll, as I haven&amp;#39;t really tested much &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mickgardner.com/2012/12/an-introduction-to-static-site.html&quot;&gt;other platforms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, if you are working on Jekyll without support from a front-end programmer, you&amp;#39;d better know some HTML, CSS, and Javascript, otherwise you will either get stuck or will be significantly limited in what you can do. My abilities with these programming languages are fairly limited, and so I can introduce small modifications to existing code, but am not anywhere near being a knowledgeable about them. What this means in practice is that my main strategy to learn Jekyll is to look at what others have done with their blogs, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Sites&quot;&gt;tons of examples&lt;/a&gt;, and then steal chunks of code from each of them. An essential point here is to test locally, which is &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/usage/&quot;&gt;pretty easy to do&lt;/a&gt; with Jekyll. This means I can grab the documentation or any random piece of code and check what it does within a matter of seconds. For the geek crowd, this is probably the single most interesting aspect of Jekyll, as even though I am no CSS/HTML/JS programmer, I can start learning in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now you might be asking what is it that Jekyll can do that you can&amp;#39;t get accomplished with &lt;a href=&quot;http://wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;WordPress&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blogger.com/&quot;&gt;Blogger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and the like? Well, if you are good you can probably do anything with any platform, including the items that will follow. But here is what I see as advantages on my own workflow, bearing in mind that some of these items will repeat what I included in my previous post about Markdown, but now in a context specific to blog posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular Expressions - since my drafts and posts are all written in markdown stored in a local directory, while writing a post I am constantly searching them. For example, have I written about that topic before, am I repeating myself, did I have previous notes on another draft that I could merge here? Regular expressions are a fantastic way to search across files, and having them in text is a big plus since I can manipulate them with &lt;a href=&quot;https://tutsplus.com/lesson/regular-expressions-in-sublime/&quot;&gt;Sublime Text very easily&lt;/a&gt;. In my specific case this is specially helpful since I tend to take a ton of notes for future posts, right now with 309 drafts ranging from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rpietro/rpietro.github.io/tree/master/_drafts&quot;&gt;single lines to drafts only missing a few things before being ready to go out&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Versioning - my whole blog is versioned on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rpietro/rpietro.github.io&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, which first and foremost means that I don&amp;#39;t have to worry about losing anything if my computer crashes. The other advantage is that I will often refer people to my draft posts on github and ask for feedback before I get the final version out. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R Markdown - I am currently preparing a series of posts about lifelong learning based on very large data sets in education, and here is probably where Jekyll shines. Simply put, I can use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rstudio.com/ide/docs/authoring/using_markdown&quot;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; to directly connect my posts to my data an then make use of some of the fantastic graphic packages in R such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://rcharts.io/&quot;&gt;rCharts&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/googleVis/index.html&quot;&gt;googleVis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ggplot2.org/&quot;&gt;ggplot2&lt;/a&gt;, among others. Like in reproducible research articles, this is specially good since I can update my blog posts on the fly, meaning that i can just add or correct an analysis and the changes are immediately online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Semantic citations - I haven&amp;#39;t started using &lt;a href=&quot;http://speroni.web.cs.unibo.it/cgi-bin/lode/req.py?req=http:/purl.org/spar/cito&quot;&gt;CiTO&lt;/a&gt; yet, but will likely start in the next few weeks. In nutshell, the idea is to use Carl Boettiger&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://carlboettiger.info/2012/05/30/knitcitations.html&quot;&gt;knitcitations&lt;/a&gt; and Tyler Rinker&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/reports/index.html&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; packages so that my links to citations can be connected to a wide range of information on that reference. For example, while citing a paper on clinical trial my link could also contain information on a related database such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://clinicaltrials.gov/&quot;&gt;ClinicalTrials.gov&lt;/a&gt;, all using the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkeddata.org/&quot;&gt;Linked Open Data&lt;/a&gt;. More on this in the future ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reuse - this happens to me almost every day, where I will grab text from one of my previous reports, papers, or slides, and then just throw bits and pieces it in a blog post. The format is identical across them, and so there is no hassle. Of course, I am making extensive use of simple search or Regular Expressions here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Translation - I just started what I hope will become a series of bilingual posts in English and Portuguese, which are then linked to language-specific Facebook group pages for researchers around the world. My workflow is then to write in English first, throw my text file on &lt;a href=&quot;http://translate.google.com/toolkit/&quot;&gt;Google Translator Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;, edit whatever the automatic translation might have gotten wrong, and I am literally done within a few minutes. Here again, having a blog post in Markdown makes it real fast and effective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No backend database - here the argument is that a static site is safer since there is no way for the blog to be attacked through a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL_injection&quot;&gt;SQL injection&lt;/a&gt;. While I think that the odds of somebody wanting to hack my blog are pretty remote - hey, the whole content is github, just fork it - for me this is more of a theoretical advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, just to restate what I said before, I am not claiming that any the items above cannot be included in a different workflow using one of the simpler blogging platforms. Hey, different folks different strokes, and Jekyll simply works for me ... at least until I find something cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Orientando pesquisadores: O começo de uma série de artigos</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/28/coaching-posts/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/28/coaching-posts</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-NFPD8IREMX4/UkLT_E35bCI/AAAAAAAA4Uk/VdQPKKT90To/w805-h403-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;title&gt; Orientando pesquisadores: O começo de uma série de artigos &lt;/title&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estou começando uma série de posts que sobre sugestões práticas para pesquisadores. Minha experiência decorre de ter &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=F5m0nQoAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;publicado em pesquisas clínica&lt;/a&gt; por muitos anos, além de ter conduzido um programa de treinamento focado em professores juniores na Duke University e algumas outras instituições. Isso significa que os posts frequentemente vão usar exemplos relacionados com a área biomédica e análise de dados, mas acredito que a maioria do conteúdo pode ser extrapolado para outras áreas de pesquisa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cada uma destes posts estará disponível em Inglês e Português, geralmente postados em dias consecutivos. Os posts também serão publicados nas respectivas paginas do Facebook, nas suas versões global e brasileira, a página brasileira &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/groups/578812732155954/?bookmark_t=group&quot;&gt;já estando disponível&lt;/a&gt;. Outras línguas podem vir a aparecer posteriormente caso os posts gerem interesse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mas chega de conversa, mãos a obra ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;escrito por Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Coaching researchers: Beginning a series of posts</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/27/coaching_posts/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data,/facebook/2013/09/27/coaching_posts</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-NFPD8IREMX4/UkLT_E35bCI/AAAAAAAA4Uk/VdQPKKT90To/w805-h403-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am starting a series of posts I plan on publishing about practical suggestions for researchers. My experience stems from having &lt;a href=&quot;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=F5m0nQoAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;published in clinical and health services research&lt;/a&gt; for many years, as well as having run a coaching program targeting junior faculty members at Duke University and a few other institutions. All this means is that my posts will frequently use examples related to the biomedical and data sciences, but I also believe that most of the content can be extrapolated to other research areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these posts will be available in English and Portuguese versions, usually posted in consecutive days. They will also be published to the respective Global and Brazilian versions of a Facebook Group page, the Brazilian page [already being available]](https://www.facebook.com/groups/578812732155954/?bookmark_t=group). Other languages might follow depending on whether the posts generate some interest. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough said, let&amp;#39;s get to work ...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>GiveDirectly libations</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/26/givedirectly_libations/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/26/givedirectly_libations</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LJRJzeuK15Q/Ujx5wKJIJFI/AAAAAAAA4LE/C4LZ_gPyNHU/w707-h481-no/fractals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ve probably heard of people who floss in the shower just because it creates an automatic habit. So, along &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.brandeis.edu/%7Eteuber/singermag1.html&quot;&gt;Peter Singer&amp;#39;s proposal&lt;/a&gt; that we should all donate money to people who didn&amp;#39;t have the same opportunities we did, I am proposing the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/give.php&quot;&gt;GiveDirectly&lt;/a&gt; libations. Here is how it works: You simply place the GiveDirectly link on the top of your bookmark, making it visible at all times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Qr-jEqqbGuo/Ujx2socEoMI/AAAAAAAA4Kk/rxMBxUOShwU/w454-h141-no/Screen+Shot+2013-09-20+at+12.23.12+PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, every time you feel like you have to ask your gods for support or strength or hope or simply luck, you go ahead and make a GiveDirectly libation by donating some money. The quantity is proportional to how much you might want to get your gods on your side, some of them might be picky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveDirectly is one of the best donation sites, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.givedirectly.org/give.php&quot;&gt;90 to 93% of your donation being transferred to the people who need the money&lt;/a&gt;. This will allow them to buy food, get better shelter, learn something, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givedirectly.org/faqs.php&quot;&gt;do whatever they think their top priority might be&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Shinto, situated cognition, and monism</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/25/shinto_monism_learning/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/25/shinto_monism_learning</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/--0Nq3O2KBnQ/Ujpbfxsl2NI/AAAAAAAA4JM/T2C3ycZ6gWY/w480-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An upfront disclosure: I am agnostic. By that I mean that I am indifferent to whether gods might or not exist, whether there might be something after what we know as life, and other concepts that are typically attributed to the realm of religion. An important distinction, I am not an atheist, meaning that I don&amp;#39;t deny the existence of gods. I am simply indifferent: Whether they might or not exist is simply not a concern of mine. But in being agnostic I have a deep respect for the power religion has on human beings and how deeply it affects literally all of us, whether you might follow any religion, be atheist or an agnostic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that disclosure out of the way, one of the most interesting concepts I&amp;#39;ve found in religious movements is the idea of integration with the whole universe. I was first introduced to the concept during a period in which I practiced &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aikido&quot;&gt;Aikido&lt;/a&gt; for a year or so. Every class had a practice of the martial art as a physical exercise, but also short lectures on the importance of being integrated with the universe in order to execute the Aikido movements. Briefly, one of the main concepts behind Aikido is that you don&amp;#39;t fight &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; somebody, but you instead let the energy of your opponents be directed against them. In order to do this, as my Aikido instructor always said, when the energy comes to you, you simply dissipate it by letting it go through. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How effective Aikido is as a martial art for street fighting is beyond the point of this post, but the point I want to make is that the concept of being integrated with the universe and participating in an overarching energy flow seem to have gotten to Aikido from &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shinto&quot;&gt;Shinto&lt;/a&gt;. The concept is actually spread to a number of areas that have no connection to either Shinto or Aikido, a very recent example being &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkour&quot;&gt;Parkour&lt;/a&gt;, where people get through city barriers such as eight feet walls not by attacking them but actually &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aAhPaiajwDY&quot;&gt;moving in harmony with them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps what is common to Aikido, Shinto and Parkour is the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monism&quot;&gt;Monism&lt;/a&gt;, or the concept that there is a unity that is inherent to all things. Where learning comes into the scene, I think, is with the concepts of using &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Situated_cognition&quot;&gt;situated cognition&lt;/a&gt; permeate the learning process. I have covered some of these concepts in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/07/29/shallows_medieval/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, but one example would be that learning is not about simply absorbing concepts, but it is instead about interacting with your environment to produce some kind of outcome. For example, rather than just learning a programming language, students will also learn how to properly ask other programmers for help or how to search for the latest tools that might help beyond what they learned during the course. In another situation, rather than simply learning about, say, racial disparities, one would take a course as an opportunity to be coached while actively working with a community to address sources of disparity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point in all of this is that the distinction between the concepts underlying religion, the sciences, humanities and likely anything humans touch is very subtle. Perhaps this is why I think that those strongly arguing in favor of a certain religion or against all religions are probably mistaken. Just look around and you will see religious concepts permeating all we do, learning included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Merrienboer, whole tasks and the learning ladder</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/24/sequencing_ladder/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/24/sequencing_ladder</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-9M89ShrDfCI/UjnxONF95nI/AAAAAAAA4H8/19ksRO9GP20/w480-h680-no/fractal2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/30/whole_task_ladder/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I have argued that while I agree with Merrienboer&amp;#39;s concept of whole tasks as an essential component in the learning process, as students increase their skill levels, they might need to step out of whole tasks to focus on narrower sectors of a given task. The latter is called a learning ladder, where experts receive only particular sectors of a given whole task where there are unusual problems. Because these problems are unusual, experts continue to accumulate experience with interesting problems, ultimately honing their skills even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I failed to mention, however, is that although the learning ladder and the whole task principle are somewhat at odds, the ladder certainly aligns with Merrieboer&amp;#39;s sequencing concept. In Merrienboer&amp;#39;s terminology, sequencing means that whole tasks should be made progressively more complex. What the learning ladder brings to the table is simply the practical realization that if complexity levels keep going up, it is no longer feasible for the student to focus on everything, but more practical to let other team members deal with the every day components of the whole task, while the expert deals with the unusual and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Need for evidence-based policy making in education</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/23/eb_policy_making/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/23/eb_policy_making</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/-V2EmCX1ceMg/UjnxOXj6gJI/AAAAAAAA4IA/k88cluJk3Uk/w480-h680-no/fractal3.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/81Ka8i8u43W&quot;&gt;posted something on Google plus&lt;/a&gt; where I argued that the sources behind educational policy making should contain at least some degree of data. In our day and age, it would be naive to think that policy making can be entirely based on data for at least a few reasons: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Policy-Making-Education-Holistic-Approach-Response/dp/1607091615/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1379477791&amp;amp;sr=8-3&amp;amp;keywords=policy+making+in+education&quot;&gt;Studies have shown over and again&lt;/a&gt; that educational policy making is primarily driven by personal interests of those in the top ranks of each national government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We simply don&amp;#39;t have enough data, experimental or observational, to cover all the data needs to create evidence-based policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To think of data as something objective and interest-free is highly misguided. The very act of designing a data collection or experiment already contains an intention to &lt;a href=&quot;http://rpietro.github.io/situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/08/12/university_dilemma/&quot;&gt;demonstrate a few things and hide others&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these three points out of the way, I would argue that collecting some data using reproducible standards is at least something that can be criticized, while a mere opinion based on vested interests is hard to dissect. For example, if your data was collected in a reproducible manner I can criticize whatever aspect of it and try to do better, but if a politician simply states that something has to be done in a certain way because &lt;em&gt;that&amp;#39;s the right thing to do&lt;/em&gt;. The latter can&amp;#39;t be argued about since the person who stated it is the most powerful stakeholder in the decision making process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Ben Gunn, social extension, and implications for learning</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/22/bengunn/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/22/bengunn</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-SvK1_5pQoGg/UjnxOdF3akI/AAAAAAAA4IE/Ccl-LgNEY1Q/w480-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently read a very interesting article where a journalist has interviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://prisonerben.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Ben Gunn&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, when Ben was 14 years old he killed another boy and was sentenced to 10 years in prison. Hi behavior while in jail was all but good, and 10 years were extended to the point where he was only released when he was 42. What is interesting about this is that while he was in jail he not only graduated from college, but went on to a MSc and started a PhD. In his blog he raises a fascinating discussion by lively describing situations he faced while in prison, making us question whether our prison system is doing society a service or just simply educating people to be better criminals than they were before getting into that system. His text is simply superb, which attracted the attention of not only about 20 thousand followers but also of newspapers and tv channels that now have Ben serving as an expert consultant every time an issue about the prison system is brought up. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/society/2013/sep/15/ben-gunn-murder-love-life-after-prison&quot;&gt;full interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That whole story is already interesting in and of itself, but in the interview Ben raises a point that I find simply fascinating. He claims to be lost after having left prison, since he doesn&amp;#39;t understand the rules by which people play. Rules while in prison were clear, but outside why do we do the things we do? In other words, if you are a blogger with 20 thousand followers and consults for major news channels, why does it matter? In other words, what is the rat wheel in which society places us all to make us believe that the goals set for ourselves are worth pursuing? The interesting thing is that by Ben being an outsider and already an adult, it will be hard for him to buy into these fictitious reasons we keep fabricating for ourselves to get us out of bed in the morning. Ideas of meaning in our careers, or an ultimate goal that we keep pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the rat wheel/meaning topic is relevant for learning in at least two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social extension: No matter much we might believe that we are individually in charge of our own goals, we are not. What is perceived to be an individual goal of mine is almost certainly something that I inherited from society, society making me believe that my goal is worth pursuing. One interpretation then is that learning has to happen in a social context. It&amp;#39;s not enough to learn a skill or simply absorb information. Learning has to happen in a context that will make that information or skill to have our so desired sense of meaning. This can be accomplished by reinforcing the skills and information with a social context that will provide a role model and help student set their &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; goals that are in reality social goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to get out of the rat wheel: A different goal is to provide students with the ability to perceive that what might seem as an individual goal is in reality something that society makes them perceive as individuals, but which in reality is imposed. Now, it would be naive to think that learning could provide students with the ability to be free from societal influences. After all, we&amp;#39;re humans and our nature seems to be to follow the flock, but perhaps an education that would at least give us a hint of what it is to think outside of the rat wheel would be a good thing ... or lead to a huge anxiety level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Need for educational scores adjusted to socio-economic factors</title>
		<link href="http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/21/adjusted_scores/"/>
		<updated>2013-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
		<id>http://rpietro.github.io//situated_cognition,/big_data/2013/09/21/adjusted_scores</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0IcrIVRSBlc/UjZmrIMKgHI/AAAAAAAA33g/omCU3nWv_r0/w1000-h680-no/fractal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oecd.org/&quot;&gt;OECD(Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development)&lt;/a&gt; has been releasing a number of statistics on education for many years. In their reports, comparisons are made across different countries in relation to, among many other things, the effectiveness of their national education systems. What we tend to forget, however, is that education is not an isolated factor, meaning that educational performance will depend on a number of socio-economic factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about this in the comments to one of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/106268032364497388036/posts/59orarBgrRP&quot;&gt;posts on Google+&lt;/a&gt;, but the concept is that educational indices should be statistically adjusted to socio-economic factors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me establish an analogy with healthcare: If I am a physician treating very sick patients, the complication rate of my patients will be substantially higher than those of somebody treating otherwise healthy patients. Does that mean that I am a bad doctor? No, simply means that my patients are sicker. Bringing this example back to education, the fact that a developing or emerging country has bad educational indices does not necessarily mean that they have a bad educational policy, but it might mean that they are doing the best possible job they can given the local socio-economic situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to generate these adjusted educational index, one would have to combine datasets containing information from education, economics, healthcare, and any other sources that might provide insight on factors that might downplay educational performance. Such a &lt;em&gt;Learning Observatory&lt;/em&gt; would have to have the ability to combine data in different formats (CSV, JSON, XML, free text, RDF, among others), always keeping in mind what the information needs of educational policy makers might be in order to put together policies aligned with their local situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by Ricardo Pietrobon&lt;/p&gt;
Included file 'rss_footer.html' not found in _includes directory</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>